<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stumbling-stone and rock of offence, as it hath been in all ages both to Jew &amp; Gentile, Christ Jesus, the power of God and the wisdom of God opened to the understanding of the simple in the answers to these questions, viz, what Christ Jesus is, what the stumbling-stone and rock of offence, how he hath been, and is, the rock of offence and stone of stumbling in all ages, wherefore it hath been and is so in all ages, or the reason of the thing, what's the end of the Lord in all, or his designe therein / by Geo. Bishope.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28241</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13571264</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100369</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240912150</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11094</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13571264</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100369)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 836:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stumbling-stone and rock of offence, as it hath been in all ages both to Jew &amp; Gentile, Christ Jesus, the power of God and the wisdom of God opened to the understanding of the simple in the answers to these questions, viz, what Christ Jesus is, what the stumbling-stone and rock of offence, how he hath been, and is, the rock of offence and stone of stumbling in all ages, wherefore it hath been and is so in all ages, or the reason of the thing, what's the end of the Lord in all, or his designe therein / by Geo. Bishope.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100369:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100369:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>TUMBLING-STONE AND Rock of Offence, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath been in</hi> all <hi>Ages both to</hi> Jew <hi>&amp;</hi> Gentile, <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Power <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>and the</hi> Wisdom <hi>of</hi> God: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ned to the Understanding of the Simple, in the Answers to</hi> these <hi>Questions;</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <list>
                     <item>What Christ Jesus is?</item>
                     <item>What the Stumbling-Stone, and Rock of Offence?</item>
                     <item>How he hath been, (and is) the Rock of Offence, and Stone of Stumbling in all Ages?</item>
                     <item>Wherefore it hath been (and is so) in all Ages? Or the Reason of the thing.</item>
                     <item>What's the End of the Lord in all, Or his Designe therein?</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEO. BISHOPE.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>NDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Robert Wilson, 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100369:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100369:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Stumbling-Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Am about a <hi>Thing</hi> of the <hi>Greatest Weight,</hi> though thought <hi>more</hi> easie by the <hi>Eye</hi> that sees <hi>not</hi> the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which are <hi>Spiritually</hi> Discerned. Viz. <hi>Christ Jesus, the Power of God, and the Wisdom of God, as he hath been (and is) in all Ages both to Jew and Gentile a Rock of Offence, and a Stone of Stumbling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Manifest <hi>this</hi> to the Understanding of the <hi>Simple, I shall</hi> shew,</p>
            <list>
               <item>First, <hi>What Christ Jesus is?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>What the Stumbling-stone, and Rock of Offence?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>How he hath been (and is) the Rock of Offence, and Stone of Stumbling both to Jew and Gentile in all Ages?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, <hi>Wherefore it hath been (and is) so in all Ages? Or the Reason of the thing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifthly, <hi>What</hi>'s <hi>the End of the Lord in all, or his Design there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>First, <hi>What Christ Jesus is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> And here it may seem strange that <hi>I</hi> put forth <hi>such</hi> a Question as <hi>this;</hi> and pretend to <hi>Answer</hi> it as a <hi>thing</hi> of <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Weight;</hi> seeing that <hi>every</hi> One Professes <hi>Him</hi> in <hi>Words,</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> believe in <hi>his</hi> Name. But before <hi>I</hi> have done, it will Appear a <hi>thing</hi> of as <hi>great</hi> Weight as <hi>I</hi> have said; and as <hi>hard</hi> a <hi>thing</hi> to know <hi>his</hi> Name, or to believe therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> then, <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> is the <hi>Power of God,</hi> and the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and this is that which <hi>I</hi> said before, and which <hi>Paul</hi> spake as aforesaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. Even <hi>the Wisdom of God in a Mystery; Even the hidden Wisdom which God Ordained before the World unto Our Glory: Which none of the Princes of this World knew; for had they known it, they would not have Crucified the Lord of Glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 7, 8. The <hi>Mystery which hath been hill from Ages and from Generations, but now is made Manifest to his Saints. To whom God would make known, what is the Riches of</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100369:3"/>
               <hi>the Glory of this Mistery among the Gentiles, which is Christ in You the hope of Glory. Whom We Preach, Warning Every Man in all wisdom, that VVe may present Every Man perfect in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, whereunto I also labour, striving, according to his working, which worketh in me Mightily,</hi> Col. 1. 26, 27, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>Now, whosoever cometh to know <hi>him</hi> to be the <hi>Wisdome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> must come to know <hi>this</hi> Mistery which hath been <hi>hid</hi> from <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Generations,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> Mistery <hi>[in]</hi> them, and what is the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Mistery <hi>[in]</hi> them, which hath been <hi>hid</hi> from <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Generations,</hi> but is now made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest to <hi>his</hi> Saints. Viz. <hi>Christ [in] them the hope of Glory. But, whom say ye that I am?</hi> (said <hi>Christ</hi> to <hi>his</hi> Disciples, Mat. 16. 15.) <hi>And</hi> Simon Peter <hi>answered and said, Thou art Christ the Son of the Living God. And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou</hi> Simon Bar-jonah, <hi>for flesh and blood hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it unto Thee, but my Father which is in heaven. And I say also unto Thee, That thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock will I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell shall not prevail against it. And I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven, and whatsoever thou shalt bind on Earth shall be bound in Heaven, and whatsoever thou shalt loose on Earth, shall be loosed in Heaven,</hi> Vers. 16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>And <hi>he</hi> is the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>Gospel of Christ is the Power of God unto Salvation, to Every One that believeth, to the Jew first, and also to the Gentile; for therein is the Righteousness of God Revealed from Faith to Faith; as it is written, The Just shall live by Faith,</hi> Rom. 1. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> Christ is <hi>[in]</hi> You, <hi>except ye be Reprobates. Know ye not that Christ is [in] You Except ye be Reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 5. And <hi>Christ</hi> being <hi>[in]</hi> You who is the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is it not a <hi>great</hi> Mistery that <hi>you</hi> know <hi>him</hi> not; Even a <hi>Mistery</hi> hid from <hi>Ages,</hi> and <hi>Generations,</hi> but now <hi>made</hi> manifest? And the <hi>Gospel</hi> being the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> unto <hi>Salvation,</hi> and <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> 1 Thes. 2. 9. Is it not a wonderful thing, that <hi>people</hi> should not Know <hi>him</hi> who stand in <hi>Need</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> when as <hi>he</hi> is <hi>[in]</hi> them, and <hi>they</hi> profess <hi>him?</hi> But <hi>he</hi> is the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> unto <hi>Salvation,</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100369:3"/>
               <hi>Every</hi> One <hi>(onely)</hi> who believe in <hi>his</hi> Name, and unto <hi>such (onely)</hi> whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> is the <hi>Righteousness of God (Christ Jesus)</hi> which is in the <hi>Gospel</hi> revealed from <hi>Faith</hi> to <hi>Faith. He that hath seen me hath seen the Fatber,</hi> said <hi>Christ</hi> to <hi>Philip,</hi> John 17. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He is the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>World;</hi> the <hi>true</hi> Light that <hi>lighteth Every</hi> Man that <hi>cometh</hi> into the <hi>World, John</hi> 19. In whom was <hi>Life,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> was the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Men:</hi> and the <hi>Light</hi> shineth in <hi>Darkness,</hi> but the <hi>Darkness</hi> comprehended it <hi>not. By</hi> whom <hi>all</hi> things were made, and <hi>without</hi> whom was not <hi>any</hi> thing made that <hi>was</hi> made: who <hi>was</hi> in the <hi>beginning</hi> with <hi>God;</hi> who was with <hi>God;</hi> who was <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>same</hi> which <hi>was</hi> in the <hi>beginning;</hi> which was with <hi>God;</hi> which was <hi>God;</hi> which <hi>was</hi> made <hi>Flesh,</hi> and dwelt among <hi>Us</hi> (said the <hi>Apostle)</hi> and <hi>we</hi> beheld <hi>his</hi> Glory, the <hi>Glory</hi> as of the <hi>onely</hi> begotten of the <hi>Father full</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Truth, John</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 14. Of which <hi>John</hi> came for a <hi>Witness;</hi> (the <hi>Man</hi> that was sent from <hi>God,</hi> whose <hi>Name</hi> was <hi>John)</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> Witness of the <hi>Light,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> Men through <hi>him</hi> might believe; who was not <hi>[that]</hi> Light but was sent to <hi>bear</hi> Witness of <hi>that</hi> Light, <hi>vers.</hi> 6, 7, 8. But <hi>I am the Light of the World</hi> (saith <hi>Christ,</hi> John 8. 12.) <hi>he that followeth me shall not walk in Darkness, but shall have the Light of Life:</hi> And, <hi>this is</hi> [the] <hi>Condemnation, that Light is come into the World, and Men love Darkness rather then Light, because their Deeds are Evil; for Every One that doth Evil hateth the Light; neither cometh to the Light least his Deeds should be reproved; but he that doth Truth cometh to the Light, that his Deeds may be made manifest that they are wrought in God,</hi> Joh. 13. 19, 20, 21. And <hi>ye will not come unto me</hi> (saith <hi>he</hi> to the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees,</hi> John 5. 40.) that <hi>ye might have Life;</hi> And in <hi>him was Life,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> was the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Men.</hi> That was the <hi>true</hi> Light that <hi>lighteth Every</hi> Man which <hi>cometh</hi> into the <hi>World,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> Light is <hi>[within]</hi> The <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> is the <hi>Eye;</hi> if <hi>thine</hi> Eye be <hi>single thy</hi> whole body is <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Light;</hi> but if <hi>thine</hi> Eye be <hi>Evil, thy</hi> whole body shall be <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Darkness.</hi> If therefore <hi>that</hi> Light that is <hi>[in]</hi> you be <hi>Darkness,</hi> how <hi>great</hi> is <hi>that</hi> Darkness? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 23. But <hi>ye</hi> Brethren are not in <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100369:4"/> that <hi>that</hi> Day should overtake <hi>you</hi> as a <hi>Thief: ye</hi> are <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> and the <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Day; We</hi> are not of the <hi>Night;</hi> nor of <hi>Darkness,</hi> 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5. 4, 5. For <hi>ye</hi> were <hi>sometimes</hi> Darkness, but now are <hi>ye</hi> Light <hi>[in]</hi> the <hi>Lord;</hi> Walk as <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Light, Ephes.</hi> 5. 8. And <hi>God</hi> who hath <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>shine</hi> out of <hi>Darkness;</hi> hath <hi>shined [in]</hi> our hearts to give the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God [in]</hi> the <hi>face</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. And <hi>I will</hi> give <hi>him</hi> for a <hi>Covenant</hi> to the <hi>People;</hi> for a <hi>Light</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> To <hi>open</hi> the <hi>Blind</hi> Eyes; to <hi>bring</hi> out the <hi>Prisoners</hi> from the <hi>Prison;</hi> and them that sit <hi>[in]</hi> Darkness out of the <hi>Prison</hi> house, <hi>Isa.</hi> 42. 6, 7. To give <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>them</hi> that sit in <hi>Darkness,</hi> and the <hi>shadow</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and to guide our feet <hi>in</hi> the Way of <hi>Peace, Luke</hi> 1. 79.</p>
            <p>Now, the <hi>Light</hi> is that which <hi>makes</hi> manifest <hi>every</hi> thing. For <hi>all</hi> things that are <hi>reproved</hi> are <hi>made</hi> manifest by the <hi>Light.</hi> For, <hi>whatsoever</hi> doth <hi>make</hi> manifest is <hi>Light;</hi> Therefore <hi>he</hi> saith, <hi>Awake thou that sleepest, and Arise from the Dead, and Christ shall give thee Light, Ephes.</hi> 5. 13. Therefore <hi>Judge</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before the <hi>time,</hi> until the <hi>Lord</hi> come who both will <hi>bring</hi> to <hi>Light</hi> the <hi>hidden</hi> things of <hi>Darkness,</hi> and will <hi>make</hi> manifest the <hi>Counsells</hi> of the <hi>hearts,</hi> and then shall <hi>every</hi> man have <hi>Praise</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. And <hi>I saw No Temple therein, for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb, are the Temple of it. And the City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moone to shine in it; for the Glory of God did Lighten it; and the Lamb is the Light thereof. And the Nations of them which are saved shall walk in the Light thereof, and the Kings of the Earth do bring their Glory, and Honour into it. And the Gates thereof shall not be shut at all by Day, for there shall be no Night there. And they shall bring the Glory, and Honour of the Nations into it. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> there shall in no wise enter into it any thing that desileth; neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whatsoever worketh Abomination, Or maketh a Lie, but they which are written in the Lamb's Book of Life: This John saw,</hi> Revel. 21. 22. to the end. And <hi>there shall be no Night there, and they need no Candle, neither Light of the Sun; for the Lord God giveth them Light; and they shall Reign for Ever and Ever,</hi> Revel. 22. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He is the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace. For unto Us a Child i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100369:4"/>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn, unto Us a Son is given, and his Name shall be called Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Counsellor, the Mighty God, the Everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace; of the encrease of his Government and Peace there shall be no End; upon the Throne of David, and upon his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to Order it, and to Establish it with Judgement, and with Justice from henceforth Even for Ever,</hi> Isa. 9. 6, 7. And, <hi>Peace I leave with you, My Peace I give unto you; Not as the World give I Peace unto you,</hi> John 14. 27. And, <hi>these things have I spoken unto you that [in] me ye might have Peace, in the World ye shall have Tribulation, but be of good Cheer I have Overcome the World,</hi> John 16. 33.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>this</hi> Peace is <hi>[within.] Be careful in nothing, but in Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing by Prayer, and Supplication, and Thanksgiving, let your Requests be made known unto God. And the Peace of God which passeth all Understanding shall keep your hearts, and Minds through Christ Jesus,</hi> Phil. 4. 6, 7. And <hi>this</hi> Man shall be <hi>the</hi> Peace, when the <hi>Assyrian</hi> shall <hi>come</hi> into <hi>Our Land,</hi> and when <hi>he</hi> shall tread in <hi>Our</hi> Pallaces, then shall <hi>We</hi> raise against <hi>him seven</hi> Shepherds, and <hi>Eight</hi> Principal <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> shall <hi>wast</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Assyria</hi> with the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Nimrod</hi> in the <hi>Entrances</hi> thereof. Thus shall <hi>he</hi> Deliver <hi>Us</hi> from the <hi>Asy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> when <hi>he</hi> cometh into <hi>Our</hi> Land, and when <hi>he</hi> treadeth within <hi>Our</hi> Borders, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5. 5, 6. And the <hi>Lord</hi> saith of <hi>Levi, My Covenant was with him,</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>I gave them to him for the fear wherewith he feared me, and was afraid before my Name,</hi> Mal. 2. 5. And <hi>I Create the Fruit of the Lips</hi> (saith the <hi>Lord) Peace, Peace, to him that is afar off, and to him that is near,</hi> saith the <hi>Lord; and I will heal him,</hi> Isa. 57. 19. And <hi>I will also make their Officers Peace, and their Exactors Righteousness,</hi> Isa. 60. 17. And, <hi>behold I will Extend Peace to her like a River, and the Glory of the Gentiles like a Flowing stream; then shall ye suck, Ye shall be born on her sides, and be dandled upon her Knees,</hi> Isa. 66. 12. And, <hi>You now therefore have sorrow, but I will see you again, and your heart shall Rejoyce; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d your Joy no Man taketh from you,</hi> John 16. 22. <hi>I [in] them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d thou [in] me, that they may be made Perfect in One, and that the World may know that thou hast sent me, and hast Loved them as thou hast Loved me. Father I will that they also whom thou</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100369:5"/>
               <hi>hast given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my Glory which thou hast given me; for thou Lovedst me from the Foundation of the World. O Righteous Father the World hath not known me, but I have known thee, and these have known that thou hast sent me; and I have declared unto them thy Name, and will Declare it; that the Love wherewith thou hast Loved me may be [in] them, and I [in] them,</hi> John 17. 23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He is <hi>the King of Righteousness.</hi> For, <hi>this Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisedeck Priest of the most high God, who met Abraham coming from the slaughter of the Kings, and blessed him; to whom also Abraham gave a Tenth part of all. First, being by Interpretation King of Righteousness; and after that also King of Salem, which is King of Peace,</hi> Heb. 7. 1, 2. And <hi>thou art a Priest for Ever after the Order of Melchisedeck,</hi> Psal. 110. 4.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is revealed from <hi>Faith</hi> to <hi>Faith,</hi> as it is written, <hi>The Just shall live by Faith;</hi> but the <hi>Wra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is revealed from <hi>Heaven</hi> against <hi>all Unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and <hi>Ungodliness</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> who <hi>hold</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness:</hi> Because <hi>that</hi> which is to be <hi>known</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is <hi>manifest [in]</hi> them, for <hi>God</hi> hath shewn it <hi>unto</hi> them. For the <hi>Invisible</hi> things of <hi>him</hi> from the <hi>Creation</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> are <hi>clearly</hi> seen, being understood by the <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>made,</hi> Even <hi>his</hi> Eternal <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Godhead,</hi> so that <hi>they are</hi> without Excuse. Because that when <hi>they</hi> knew <hi>God</hi> they Glorified <hi>him</hi> not as <hi>God</hi> neither were thankful, but became <hi>Vain</hi> in <hi>their</hi> Imaginations, and their <hi>foolish</hi> heart was Darkned. Professing <hi>themselves</hi> to be <hi>Wise they</hi> became fools; and changed the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi> God, into an <hi>Image</hi> made like to <hi>Corruptible</hi> Man, and to <hi>Birds,</hi> and <hi>four footed</hi> Beasts, and to <hi>Creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> things. Wherefore <hi>God</hi> gave <hi>them</hi> up also to <hi>Uncleanness,</hi> through the <hi>lusts</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Own hearts, to Dishonour <hi>their</hi> Own bodies between <hi>themselves,</hi> who changed the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>God</hi> into <hi>a Lie,</hi> and Worshipped and served the <hi>Creature</hi> more then the <hi>Creator,</hi> who is <hi>Blessed</hi> for <hi>Ever,</hi> Rom. 1. 17. to the 26. And the <hi>Righteousness</hi> which is of <hi>Faith,</hi> saith on <hi>this</hi> wise, Say not in <hi>thine</hi> heart, who shall ascend into <hi>Heaven?</hi> (that is to bring <hi>Christ</hi> from <hi>above)</hi> Or, who shall <hi>Descend</hi> into the <hi>Deep?</hi> that is, to bring up <hi>Christ</hi> from the <hi>Dead.</hi> But what saith it? The <hi>Word</hi> is nigh <hi>thee</hi> [in) <hi>thy</hi> mouth, and <hi>[in] thy</hi> heart; which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100369:5"/> is the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> which <hi>We</hi> Preach. That if <hi>thou</hi> shalt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess with <hi>thy</hi> mouth the <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> and shalt believe in <hi>thy</hi> heart, that <hi>God</hi> hath raised <hi>him</hi> from the <hi>Dead, thou</hi> shalt be saved. For, with the <hi>heart</hi> Man believeth unto <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and with the <hi>Mouth</hi> Confession is <hi>made</hi> unto <hi>Salvation.</hi> For the <hi>Scripture</hi> saith, <hi>Whosoever believeth in him shall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed;</hi> for there is <hi>No</hi> Difference between the <hi>Jew</hi> and the <hi>Greek;</hi> for the <hi>same</hi> Lord Over <hi>all</hi> is rich unto <hi>all</hi> that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>him;</hi> for <hi>whosoever shall</hi> call upon the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> shall be saved. How then shall <hi>they</hi> call on <hi>him</hi> in whom <hi>they</hi> have not believed? and how shall <hi>they</hi> believe in <hi>him</hi> of whom <hi>they</hi> have not heard? and how shall <hi>they</hi> hear without a <hi>Preacher?</hi> and how shall <hi>they</hi> Preach Except <hi>they</hi> be sent? as it is written, <hi>how beautiful are the feet of them that Preach the Gospel of Peace, and bring glad tydings of tood things?</hi> but <hi>they</hi> have not <hi>all</hi> obeyed the <hi>Gospel.</hi> For <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>Lord who hath believed Our Report?</hi> So then <hi>Faith</hi> cometh by <hi>hearing,</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> But <hi>I say,</hi> have <hi>they</hi> not heard? Yes, Verily, <hi>their</hi> sound went unto <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Earth;</hi> and <hi>their</hi> words unto the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> But <hi>I say,</hi> Did not <hi>Israel</hi> know? First, <hi>Moses</hi> saith, <hi>I will provoke you unto Jealousie by them that are no People; and by a foolish Nation I will Anger you.</hi> But <hi>Isaiah</hi> is <hi>very</hi> bold, and saith, <hi>I was found of them that sought me not; I was made manifest to them that asked not after me;</hi> but to <hi>Israel</hi> he saith, <hi>All Day long I have stretched f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th my hand to a Disobedient, and Gain-saying People,</hi> Rom. 10. 6. to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He is the <hi>Blessed,</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> Potentate, <hi>God</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wise, <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords.</hi> The <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> Who <hi>onely</hi> hath <hi>Immortality,</hi> dwelling in the <hi>Light</hi> which <hi>no</hi> Man can Approach unto; whom <hi>no</hi> Man hath <hi>seen,</hi> or <hi>can see;</hi> to whom be <hi>Honour, and Power</hi> Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting, Amen. Who is <hi>Invisible,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 15. Rom. 16. 27. Revel. 1. 5. Who dwells <hi>[in] his</hi> People; As <hi>God</hi> hath said <hi>I will dwell [in] them, and walk [in] them; and I will be their G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and they shall be my People,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 16. Who <hi>standeth</hi> at the <hi>Door,</hi> and <hi>Knocks. Behold I stand at the Door and Knock, if any Man hear my Voice, and Open the Door, I will come [into]</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100369:6"/>
               <hi>him, and will Sup with him, and he with me,</hi> Revel. 3. 20. Whose <hi>People</hi> are <hi>[in]</hi> him; Whose <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>[in]</hi> God, of which <hi>he</hi> is the <hi>head;</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>first</hi> born whose <hi>Names</hi> are written <hi>[in]</hi> Heaven; Who are <hi>Redeemed</hi> from the <hi>Earth,</hi> who follow <hi>him</hi> on <hi>White</hi> horses; Who are <hi>Cloathed</hi> in <hi>white</hi> Linnen <hi>Fine</hi> and <hi>Clean;</hi> Who are not <hi>defiled</hi> with <hi>Women;</hi> A <hi>Glorious</hi> Church without <hi>Spot</hi> or <hi>Wrinckle,</hi> or <hi>any</hi> such thing, which is <hi>all</hi> Glorious <hi>[within] Sion</hi> the <hi>Perfection</hi> of <hi>Beauty,</hi> The <hi>Onely</hi> One of her that bare <hi>her,</hi> which is but <hi>One;</hi> who is <hi>all</hi> Fair, there's <hi>no</hi> Spot in her; The <hi>Bride</hi> the <hi>Lamb's</hi> Wife; The <hi>holy</hi> City; the <hi>New</hi> Jerusalem <hi>that comes down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband; Jerusalem</hi> that is <hi>above,</hi> which is <hi>Free,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Us</hi> all; A <hi>Chosen</hi> Generation; A <hi>Royal</hi> Priesthood; A <hi>holy</hi> Nation; A <hi>Peculiar</hi> People; <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> unto <hi>God;</hi> The <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>most</hi> high; The <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> The <hi>born</hi> not of <hi>Blood;</hi> Nor the <hi>will</hi> of the <hi>Flesh;</hi> Nor of the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> but of <hi>God;</hi> The <hi>Flesh</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Flesh, <hi>and Bone</hi> of his bone; The <hi>Immortal</hi> Generation which call <hi>God Father,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> them <hi>his</hi> Children; who lives for <hi>Ever;</hi> who is not ashamed to be called <hi>their</hi> God; who hath prepared for <hi>them</hi> a <hi>City;</hi> A <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Habitations;</hi> A <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Habitation;</hi> A <hi>sure</hi> Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; A <hi>hiding</hi> place from the <hi>storm;</hi> A <hi>shadow</hi> from the <hi>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, When the storm of the terrible One shall be as a Blast against the Wall;</hi> The <hi>Shadow</hi> of a <hi>Rock</hi> in a <hi>Weary</hi> Land; A <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge;</hi> A <hi>sure</hi> Defence; A <hi>high</hi> Tower, <hi>thou savest me from mine Enemies;</hi> A <hi>Rock;</hi> The <hi>Munition</hi> of <hi>Rocks; Bread th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will not fail;</hi> The <hi>Place</hi> that is <hi>higher</hi> then I; The <hi>Water of Life;</hi> The <hi>Stone;</hi> the <hi>tryed</hi> stone; The <hi>Corner Stone, Elect</hi> and <hi>Precious;</hi> the <hi>Stone which the Builders refused; The head of the Corner;</hi> The <hi>Corner</hi> Stone; The <hi>living</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, The <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> I am saith <hi>he;</hi> The <hi>Door;</hi> The <hi>Branch;</hi> The <hi>Root;</hi> The <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>off-spring</hi> of <hi>David;</hi> The <hi>Stone</hi> of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; I</hi> am; who is without <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>Dayes,</hi> or <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Life;</hi> who is of an <hi>Eternal</hi> Generation; who <hi>liveth for Ever. To whom coming as to a Living Stone, disallowed indeed of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but chosen of God, and Precious; they also as lively Stones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e built up a Spiritual house, an holy Priesthood, to offer up Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100369:6"/>
               <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rifices acceptable to God by Jesus Christ;</hi> The <hi>City</hi> into which in <hi>no</hi> wise can Enter <hi>any</hi> thing that <hi>defileth;</hi> Neither <hi>whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver worketh Abomination,</hi> or <hi>maketh</hi> a <hi>Lie;</hi> but <hi>they</hi> that are <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Lamb's</hi> book of <hi>Life;</hi> who are not <hi>Redeemed</hi> with <hi>Corruptible</hi> things, as <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> from <hi>their</hi> Vain Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation received by <hi>[Tradition]</hi> from <hi>their</hi> Fathers; but with the <hi>Precious</hi> blood of <hi>Christ;</hi> as a <hi>Lamb</hi> without <hi>blemish,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Spot;</hi> Being <hi>born</hi> again not of <hi>Corruptible</hi> Seed, but of an <hi>Incorruptible,</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which <hi>liveth</hi> and <hi>abideth</hi> for <hi>Ever. For all Flesh is grass, and all the Glory of Man as the Flower of the Grass; the Grass withereth, and the Flower fadeth, but the Word of the Lord Endureth for Ever. And this is the Word which by the Gospel is Preached unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Immortal</hi> Word which <hi>abideth</hi> for <hi>ever,</hi> which is able to <hi>save</hi> the <hi>Soul;</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which is <hi>Perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erting</hi> the <hi>Soul;</hi> The <hi>Testimony</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which is <hi>sure m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king</hi> wise the <hi>heart;</hi> The <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which are <hi>Right Rejoycing</hi> the <hi>heart;</hi> The <hi>Commandment</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which is <hi>Pure Enlightning</hi> the <hi>Eyes;</hi> The <hi>fear</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which is <hi>clean Enduring</hi> for <hi>Ever;</hi> The <hi>Judgements</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which are <hi>true</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> altogether; More to be desired then <hi>Gold,</hi> yea then <hi>much</hi> fine <hi>Gold, sweeter</hi> also then the <hi>Honey,</hi> and the <hi>Honey</hi> Comb.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heir</hi> of <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> things, <hi>by whom also the World was made;</hi> The <hi>Brightness</hi> of the <hi>Father's</hi> Glory; The <hi>Express</hi> Image of <hi>his</hi> Person; who when <hi>he</hi> had by <hi>himself</hi> Purged <hi>Our</hi> Sins, sate down on the <hi>Right</hi> hand of the <hi>Majesty</hi> on <hi>high;</hi> who is the <hi>Faithful</hi> Witness; The <hi>first</hi> begotten from the <hi>Dead;</hi> who hath <hi>loved Us</hi> and washed <hi>Us</hi> from <hi>Our</hi> Sins in <hi>his</hi> Own Blood, and made <hi>Us</hi> Kings and <hi>Priests</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Father; To whom be <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> for <hi>Ever</hi> and <hi>Ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who cometh with <hi>Clouds,</hi> and <hi>Every</hi> Eye shall see <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> also which Pierced <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> Kindreds of the Earth shall wail because of <hi>him, Amen.</hi> Who is <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega;</hi> the <hi>Beginning,</hi> and the <hi>Ending, saith the Lord;</hi> which <hi>is,</hi> and which <hi>was,</hi> and which <hi>is</hi> to come, the <hi>Almighty; Immanuel God</hi> with <hi>Us;</hi> The <hi>Child</hi> born; The <hi>Son</hi> Given; <hi>Wonderful Counsellor, the Mighty God; the Everlasting Father; The Prince</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100369:7"/>
               <hi>of Peace;</hi> Of the <hi>Increase of whose Government and Peace, there shall be no End; Ʋpon the Throne of</hi> David, <hi>and upon his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to Order it, and Establish it with Justice, and with Judgment, henceforth Even for Ever;</hi> On <hi>Whose</hi> shoulder the <hi>Government</hi> lies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Morning Star,</hi> that hath the <hi>seven</hi> Spirits of <hi>God;</hi> and the <hi>seven</hi> Stars; The <hi>Amen;</hi> The <hi>Beginning</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that hath <hi>his</hi> Eyes like a <hi>flame</hi> of <hi>fire;</hi> and <hi>his</hi> feet are like unto <hi>fine</hi> Brass; Who <hi>holdeth</hi> the <hi>seven</hi> Stars in <hi>his</hi> right hand; who <hi>walketh</hi> in the <hi>Midst</hi> of the <hi>Seven Golden</hi> Candlesticks; who <hi>hath</hi> the <hi>sharp</hi> Sword with <hi>Two</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; <hi>He</hi> that is <hi>Holy; He</hi> that is <hi>True; He</hi> that hath the <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>David; He</hi> that <hi>Openeth</hi> and <hi>no</hi> Man <hi>shutteth,</hi> and <hi>shutteth</hi> and <hi>no</hi> Man <hi>openeth; Whose</hi> Kingdom is an <hi>Everlasting</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and <hi>his</hi> Dominion that which shall <hi>never</hi> have End.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> and of <hi>Every</hi> Man, and of the <hi>Church;</hi> The <hi>Resurrection</hi> and the <hi>Life;</hi> The <hi>Bread that came Down from Heaven;</hi> the <hi>Living</hi> Bread, <hi>which whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Eateth shall never hunger;</hi> the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Life, of which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever Drinketh shall never thirst again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Word</hi> which was in the <hi>Beginning,</hi> which was with <hi>God,</hi> which was <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>same</hi> was in the <hi>Beginning</hi> with <hi>God; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> things were made by <hi>him,</hi> and without <hi>him</hi> was nothing made that was <hi>made;</hi> In <hi>him</hi> was <hi>Life,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> was the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Men:</hi> That was the <hi>true Light,</hi> that <hi>lighteth Every Man th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cometh into the VVorld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> Eternal, Immortal, who <hi>liveth</hi> for <hi>Ever,</hi> to whom be <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Praise,</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> for <hi>Ever; VVho is able to save to the uttermost, whosoever Cometh to God by him;</hi> Who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is <hi>Worthy,</hi> to whom be <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> Everlasting: Whose <hi>Throne</hi> is for <hi>Ever</hi> and <hi>Ever;</hi> The <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>whose</hi> Kingdom, is a <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>Righteousness;</hi> Who hath loved <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,</hi> and hated <hi>Iniquity.</hi> Therefore <hi>God,</hi> even <hi>his</hi> God hath Anoynted <hi>him</hi> with the <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Gladness</hi> above <hi>his</hi> Fellows, who was made <hi>little</hi> lower than the <hi>Angels</hi> for the <hi>suffering</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and is Crowned with <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who sitteth at the <hi>Right</hi> hand of <hi>God,</hi> Making Intercession for <hi>Us;</hi> Who is <hi>Our</hi> High Priest; Who is a <hi>Propitiation</hi> for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100369:7"/>
               <hi>Our</hi> sins; Who by <hi>One</hi> Offering, for <hi>Ever</hi> perfected those that are <hi>Sanctified;</hi> Who <hi>ascended</hi> far above <hi>all</hi> Heavens; Who was <hi>made</hi> not after the <hi>Law</hi> of a <hi>Carnal</hi> Commandment, but after the <hi>Power</hi> of an <hi>Endless</hi> Life; Who is <hi>set</hi> down at the <hi>Right</hi> hand of the <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Majesty</hi> in the Heavens: The <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>pitcht</hi> and not <hi>Man,</hi> who is a <hi>Faithful,</hi> and <hi>Merciful</hi> High Priest in <hi>things</hi> pertaining to <hi>God,</hi> to make <hi>Reconciliation</hi> for the <hi>sins</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> The <hi>great</hi> High Priest, who is <hi>passed</hi> into the <hi>Heavens; Jesus</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> Who is not such an <hi>High Priest,</hi> as cannot be <hi>touched</hi> with the <hi>feeling</hi> of <hi>Our</hi> Infirmities, but was in <hi>all</hi> things temped like as <hi>we</hi> are, yet without <hi>sin;</hi> Who in that <hi>he</hi> himself hath suffered <hi>being</hi> Tempted, <hi>he</hi> is able to succour <hi>them</hi> that are Tempted; Who though <hi>he</hi> were a <hi>Son,</hi> Yet learned <hi>he</hi> Obedience by the <hi>things</hi> that <hi>he</hi> Suffered; and being made <hi>Perfect,</hi> became the <hi>Author</hi> of Eternal Salvation unto <hi>all</hi> them that <hi>Obey</hi> him: Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <hi>God</hi> to be an <hi>High Priest</hi> after the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Melchisedeck,</hi> of whom <hi>I have</hi> many things to <hi>say,</hi> and <hi>hard</hi> to be Uttered; <hi>Who is come the Second time without sin unto Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Door,</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Life;</hi> The <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Living Way</hi> into the <hi>Holiest;</hi> The <hi>Only</hi> Name given under <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> by which <hi>We</hi> can be saved; The <hi>Tabernacle</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>Pitch'd,</hi> and not <hi>Man;</hi> The <hi>Altar</hi> of which <hi>they</hi> have <hi>no</hi> Right to Eat who serve the <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> An <hi>High Priest</hi> who is <hi>Holy, Harmless, Ʋndefiled, Seperate</hi> from <hi>Sinners,</hi> and made <hi>higher</hi> than the <hi>Heavens;</hi> who needeth not <hi>Dayly</hi> as those <hi>High Priests</hi> to offer up <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> first for <hi>his</hi> Own sins; and then for the <hi>People,</hi> for this <hi>he</hi> did <hi>Once</hi> when he offered up <hi>himself:</hi> For the <hi>Law</hi> maketh Men <hi>High Priests</hi> which have <hi>Infirmity;</hi> but the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which was since the <hi>Law,</hi> maketh the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who is <hi>Consecrated</hi> for <hi>Evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>New</hi> Covenant, the <hi>Law</hi> written in the <hi>Heart,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear</hi> put in the <hi>inner Parts;</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> who is <hi>greater</hi> than the <hi>Angels,</hi> being made so much <hi>better</hi> than the <hi>Angels,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Inheritance</hi> obtained a <hi>more</hi> Excellent Name than <hi>they;</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto which of the <hi>Angels</hi> said <hi>he</hi> at any time, <hi>Thou art my Son, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his Day have I begotten Thee?</hi> And again, <hi>I will be to him a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er, and he shall be to me a Son:</hi> And again, <hi>When he bringeth</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100369:8"/>
               <hi>the First Begotten into the World, he saith, And let all the Angels of God Worship him:</hi> And of the <hi>Angels he</hi> saith, <hi>Who maketh his Angels spirits, and his Ministers a flame of fire; but unto the Son he saith, Thy Throne O God Endureth for Ever: A Scepter of Righteousness is the Scepter of thy Kingdom; Thou hast loved Righteousness, and hated Iniquity; therefore God, Even thy God hath Anoynted Thee with the Oyl of Gladness above thy Fellowes: And thou Lord in the beginning hast laid the Foundation of the Earth, and the Heavens are the Works of thy hands; They sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Perish but Thou Remainest; and they all shall wax old as doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Garment, and as a Vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be Changed: but Thou art the same, and thy Years shall not fail.</hi> But to <hi>which</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> said <hi>he</hi> at any time, <hi>Sit on my righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand, until I make thine Enemies thy Footstool?</hi> Are <hi>they</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ministring Spirits sent forth for the <hi>good</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> who shall be <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>Salvation?</hi> Therefore <hi>We</hi> ought to take the <hi>more</hi> ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est heed to the <hi>things</hi> that <hi>we</hi> have heard, lest at <hi>any</hi> time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> should let <hi>them</hi> slip; for if the <hi>Word</hi> spoken by <hi>Angels</hi> was <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast,</hi> and <hi>Every</hi> Disobedience received a <hi>just</hi> Recompence of <hi>Reward,</hi> How shall <hi>we</hi> Escape if we neglect so <hi>great</hi> Salvati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, which at <hi>first</hi> began to be spoken by the <hi>Lord,</hi> and was Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto <hi>Us</hi> by <hi>them</hi> that heard <hi>him; God</hi> also <hi>bearing</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Witness</hi> both with <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> and with divers <hi>Mira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Gifts</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> according to <hi>his</hi> Own will▪ For unto the <hi>Angels</hi> hath <hi>he not</hi> put into <hi>Subjection</hi> the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to <hi>Come,</hi> of which <hi>we</hi> speak: but <hi>One</hi> in a certain <hi>place</hi> testified▪ <hi>Saying, What is Man that thou art Mindful of him? Or, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Son of Man that thou visitedst him? Thou madest him a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lower than the Angels; Thou Crownedst him with Glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Honour, and didst set him Over the Works of thy hands; T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hast put all things in Subjection under his feet; For in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all in Subjection, he left nothing that is not put under him:</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> now <hi>we</hi> see not <hi>yet all</hi> things put under <hi>him;</hi> but <hi>we</hi> see <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who was made <hi>little</hi> Lower than the <hi>Angels,</hi> for the Suffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Death,</hi> Crowned with <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour;</hi> that <hi>he</hi> by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God</hi> should taste <hi>Death</hi> for <hi>Every</hi> Man. For it beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>him</hi> for whom are <hi>all</hi> things, and by whom are <hi>all</hi> things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bringing <hi>many</hi> Sons unto <hi>Glory,</hi> to Make the <hi>Captain</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100369:8"/> Salvation <hi>Perfect</hi> through <hi>Sufferings;</hi> for both <hi>he</hi> that <hi>Sanctifieth,</hi> and they who are <hi>Sanctified,</hi> are both of <hi>One:</hi> for which Cause <hi>he</hi> is not ashamed to call <hi>them</hi> Brethren, saying, <hi>I will declare thy Name unto thy Brethren; In the Midst of the Church will I sing Praise unto thee:</hi> And again, <hi>I will put my Trust in him;</hi> And <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I and the Children which God hath given Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then <hi>this</hi> is <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> in Answer to the <hi>first</hi> Question.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Question is, <hi>What is the Stumbling Stone, and Rock of Offence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> And <hi>here</hi> again as I said before, <hi>this</hi> may seem a <hi>needless</hi> Question to be put before <hi>such</hi> a Generation of <hi>Professors,</hi> who have <hi>Each</hi> of them in <hi>their</hi> Day (that is to <hi>say, Every</hi> Profession) pretended unto <hi>this;</hi> and that <hi>their</hi> Profession hath been a <hi>Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> to that which hath been <hi>Against</hi> it: And <hi>so</hi> it may be thought a Matter of <hi>little</hi> Weight, Either to put or Answer the <hi>Question.</hi> But as <hi>I</hi> said of the <hi>Other,</hi> so <hi>I</hi> shall say of <hi>this,</hi> That it is a Matter of <hi>another</hi> manner of <hi>weight,</hi> and before <hi>I</hi> have done it will be Manifested. The <hi>STUMBLING STONE</hi> then, and <hi>ROCK</hi> of <hi>OFFENCE,</hi> that hath been (and is) in <hi>all</hi> Ages, both to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> is <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may say, <hi>How is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Answer, Not that <hi>he</hi> is so in <hi>himself,</hi> Or that <hi>he</hi> is set so of the <hi>Lord,</hi> but as it falls out to be <hi>so</hi> by reason of that in <hi>Man,</hi> which is Entred since the <hi>Fall,</hi> that raiseth <hi>him</hi> up against <hi>that</hi> which is the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Deliver</hi> Man, Unto which <hi>He</hi> is a <hi>Stumbling Stone</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> and is set <hi>so</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> that is to say, that <hi>Man</hi> may not go on smooth in his <hi>way</hi> to Destruction, but that there may be <hi>something</hi> to stand in <hi>his</hi> Way, for <hi>him</hi> to <hi>Stumble</hi> at, for to <hi>offend</hi> him, or for <hi>him</hi> to go <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst;</hi> that as a <hi>Man</hi> Drowsie in the <hi>Dark,</hi> he may fall upon it, or <hi>justle</hi> at it; Or <hi>he</hi> may be <hi>strucken</hi> by it, and so <hi>he</hi> may come to be <hi>Awake,</hi> and to <hi>Consider</hi> where <hi>he</hi> is, and whither <hi>he</hi> is going, and what leads <hi>him,</hi> as is usual in <hi>such</hi> Cases with <hi>Men</hi> in <hi>such</hi> a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Outward. Therefore the <hi>Lord</hi> saith, <hi>Behold I lay in Sion a STUMBLING STONE, and ROCK of OFFENCE, and whosoever believeth in him shall not be ashamed,</hi> Rom. 9. 33. And <hi>they</hi> stumbled at <hi>that Stumbling Stone,</hi> as it is written, as <hi>afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said,</hi> vers. 32.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100369:9"/>
            <p> Now the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd</hi> hath not laid <hi>him</hi> a <hi>STUMBLING STONE,</hi> and <hi>ROCK</hi> of <hi>OFFENCE,</hi> that is to say, that <hi>he</hi> should <hi>so</hi> be for <hi>that</hi> purpose that <hi>Men</hi> might fall, and be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oken; but that <hi>that</hi> which leads <hi>Man</hi> into <hi>Death</hi> may <hi>stumble</hi> at it; and that <hi>Man</hi> who is led into <hi>Death</hi> may stumble at it; and seeing where <hi>he</hi> is, and whither <hi>he</hi> is going, or being awakened by <hi>that</hi> which stands in <hi>his</hi> Way to Destruction, and believing in <hi>that</hi> which shews <hi>him</hi> where <hi>he</hi> is, and stops <hi>his</hi> Career, and puts <hi>him</hi> to Mind, <hi>he</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay be Delivered. Therefore <hi>he</hi> saith, <hi>Whosoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him shall not be ashamed:</hi> So that the want of believing in <hi>him</hi> whom the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid in <hi>Sion</hi> a <hi>STUMBLING STONE,</hi> and <hi>ROCK</hi> of <hi>OFFENCE,</hi> that <hi>whosoever believeth in him shall not be ashamed;</hi> is the <hi>Ground</hi> why <hi>he is</hi> unto such a <hi>ROCK</hi> of <hi>OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FENCE,</hi> and <hi>STONE</hi> of <hi>STUMBLING.</hi> But <hi>how, wherefore,</hi> and for <hi>what</hi> End, <hi>I shall</hi> by and by make manifest in Answers to the <hi>following Questions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How hath he been then</hi> (and is) <hi>in all Ages a Stone of stumbling, and Rock of Offence?</hi> which is the <hi>Third</hi> Question.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Answer;</hi> Not that <hi>he</hi> is so in <hi>his</hi> Own Nature (as before) nor that <hi>he</hi> is laid so by the <hi>Lord;</hi> but <hi>he</hi> being contrary to the Nature of <hi>that</hi> which leads <hi>Man</hi> in the fall; and is begotten in the <hi>fall; that</hi> which leads <hi>Man</hi> in the <hi>fall,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>begotten</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> by the <hi>fall;</hi> having <hi>such</hi> a near Similitude and <hi>Relation</hi> as the <hi>same</hi> Flesh and <hi>Spirit,</hi> carries <hi>Man</hi> against <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>set</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to Redeem <hi>Man</hi> out of <hi>it.</hi> That which is come to Redeem, the <hi>Lord</hi> hath set in <hi>Its</hi> Way; and against <hi>this,</hi> that which brought, and keeps Man in the <hi>fall,</hi> Leads, and by reason hereof, <hi>Man</hi> instead of heeding <hi>that</hi> which is the <hi>Loving Kindness</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to bring <hi>him</hi> back into the <hi>state</hi> in which <hi>he</hi> was before <hi>he</hi> fell, he becomes Enemy to that which is set to bring <hi>him</hi> back, and to lead <hi>him</hi> into the <hi>Way</hi> again; that so <hi>Man</hi> may be kept where <hi>he</hi> is, Even in the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Perdition,</hi> and that for <hi>Ever.</hi> For, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> being become an <hi>Enemy</hi> to that which is appointed, or laid by the <hi>Lord</hi> to Deliver <hi>him;</hi> without which there can be <hi>no</hi> Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: how <hi>he</hi> can choose (or how can it be otherwise whilst he is in this state) but miscarry. For a <hi>Man</hi> will not (willingly) be Led by <hi>that</hi> unto which <hi>he</hi> is an <hi>Enemy;</hi> And <hi>ye who were sometimes alienated, and Enemies in your Minds by wicked Works; ye now he hath Reconciled,</hi> saith <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Saints, and Faithful</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Christ,</hi> which were at <hi>Colosse,</hi> Col. 1. 2, 21. Who were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100369:9"/> sometimes <hi>such.</hi> And to the <hi>Ephesians he</hi> Writes, <hi>wherefore that ye being in times past Gentiles in the Flesh; who are called Uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, by that which is called the Circumcision in the Flesh made by hands, that at the time ye were without Christ, being Aliens from the Common-wealth of Israel, and strangers from the Covenant of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; having no hope, and without God in the World. But now in Christ Jesus; Ye who sometimes were far off, are made nigh by the Blood of Christ; For he is Our Peace who hath made both One; and hath broken down the middle Wall of Partition between Us; having abolished [in] his Flesh the [Emnity] Even the Law of Commandments contained in Ordinances, for to make [in] himself of Twaine One New Man; so making Peace, and that he might reconcile both unto God in One Body by the Cross, having slain the [Emnity] thereby; and came and Preached Peace to you which were afar off, and to them that were nigh; for through him we both have an Access by One Spirit unto the Father,</hi> Ephes. 2. 11. to the 19.</p>
            <p>Now, what can be a <hi>greater</hi> Bar against the <hi>Salvation</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> then to be <hi>raised</hi> up in <hi>Emnity</hi> against that which is to Deliver <hi>him?</hi> and what <hi>greater</hi> advantage can an <hi>Enemy</hi> have upon a <hi>Man,</hi> then to make <hi>him</hi> an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>his</hi> Deliverer? And what <hi>greater</hi> Policy, and <hi>Art</hi> can be used, then <hi>so</hi> to make a <hi>Man</hi> who is in the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Eternal</hi> Condemnation? Yet, <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>all Men</hi> by <hi>Nature;</hi> and the <hi>Condition</hi> in which the <hi>Lord</hi> finds <hi>Every</hi> Man. <hi>Viz.</hi> In <hi>Emnity</hi> against <hi>that</hi> which <hi>he</hi> hath set to Deliver <hi>him. For, if when we were [Enemies] we were reconciled by the Death of his Son; Much more being reconciled we shall be saved by his Life, And not only so, but we Joy in God through Our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have [now] received the [Atonement]</hi> Rom. 5. 10, 11. And <hi>this</hi> is <hi>Deceit</hi> indeed, and a <hi>subtile</hi> Device in the <hi>Enemy,</hi> so to make <hi>Man</hi> to that which is <hi>his</hi> Peace. And, indeed, it is <hi>hard</hi> to be believed how it is, and that a <hi>Man</hi> could <hi>possibly</hi> come to be <hi>so</hi> deceived of the <hi>Devil,</hi> till his <hi>Eyes</hi> be in <hi>Measure</hi> Opened, and <hi>he</hi> come to see <hi>how</hi> it is; and <hi>they</hi> who have come to see <hi>this</hi> his Working, have spoken of it to be a <hi>Device</hi> most subtile; for, what can be <hi>greater</hi> then by <hi>Artifices,</hi> and <hi>Paintings,</hi> to render that to be the <hi>onely</hi> Enemy to <hi>Man,</hi> and to set <hi>him</hi> against <hi>it</hi> as such, which is <hi>his</hi> choicest Friend, and without which <hi>he</hi> is Undone for <hi>Ever.</hi> A mistake, <hi>indeed,</hi> to the <hi>Purpose</hi> (as <hi>Men</hi> use to say) or with a <hi>Witness;</hi> For what can be <hi>greater,</hi> or <hi>More</hi> Desperate, then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100369:10"/> for a <hi>Man</hi> who is in the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Greatest</hi> Wound, to be led out in the <hi>highest</hi> Opposition to that which is the <hi>Onely</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy? And how can a <hi>Man</hi> be held <hi>more</hi> fast, or made <hi>more</hi> sure by an <hi>Enemy,</hi> then to be possessed against <hi>such</hi> a One with the <hi>greatest</hi> hatred, and to be raised up <hi>so</hi> against <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>his</hi> dearest Friend, Even <hi>him</hi> without whom <hi>he</hi> cannot be Delivered? yet this is the case as to <hi>many. They</hi> are fallen from <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression;</hi> that which led them into the <hi>fall,</hi> holds <hi>them</hi> in <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity;</hi> willing <hi>they</hi> are there to continue, because <hi>they</hi> see not where <hi>they</hi> are, nor what doth lead <hi>them.</hi> Yet in a <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> they are; and the <hi>Way</hi> they walk in, is the <hi>Path</hi> to <hi>Hell.</hi> Now <hi>they</hi> cannot come to see <hi>this</hi> their state; Nor be Redeemed out of it, but by that which shews <hi>them</hi> it, and stands in <hi>their</hi> Way to check <hi>their</hi> Career, and stop <hi>their</hi> course unto the <hi>Pit;</hi> which is <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>Every</hi> Man; who is the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> which <hi>Lighteth Every Man that cometh into the World;</hi> which is come to Redeem <hi>Man</hi> out of the <hi>fall,</hi> and from the <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>him</hi> that hates <hi>him,</hi> of his Enemy; and <hi>God</hi> hath laid <hi>him</hi> in <hi>Sion,</hi> (in <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him)</hi> for that purpose, which <hi>Answereth</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> as a <hi>STUMBLING STONE,</hi> a <hi>ROCK</hi> of <hi>OFFENCE,</hi> which whensoever <hi>Man</hi> is Tempted to Evil, shews <hi>him</hi> Evil; the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which hath appeared unto <hi>all Men,</hi> Even the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance</hi> of <hi>Evil,</hi> and stands in <hi>his</hi> Way to <hi>Evil;</hi> So that against <hi>this</hi> Rock <hi>he</hi> must go; <hi>he</hi> that is the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Ages;</hi> which stands in <hi>his</hi> Way to offend <hi>him;</hi> to keep <hi>him</hi> of; and at <hi>this</hi> stone <hi>he</hi> must stumble, and <hi>over</hi> it <hi>he</hi> must go if <hi>he</hi> doth do <hi>Evil.</hi> Now for <hi>such</hi> to be raised up in <hi>Emnity</hi> against <hi>this;</hi> for the <hi>Enemy</hi> who hath <hi>them</hi> in Evil, and leads <hi>them</hi> into Evil <hi>so</hi> to Deceive them; as to set <hi>them</hi> in Hatred against <hi>that</hi> which shews <hi>them</hi> Evil, and the <hi>very</hi> Appearance of it, and stands in <hi>their</hi> Way thereunto, and so into the <hi>Pit;</hi> and strives with <hi>them</hi> that <hi>they</hi> may not Perish, which <hi>they</hi> know is <hi>Truth,</hi> and that that is <hi>Evil</hi> which it <hi>stands</hi> against, and that <hi>Evil</hi> is the <hi>Way</hi> unto the <hi>Pit,</hi> unto which <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers</hi> that of <hi>God</hi> which is <hi>in them;</hi> which <hi>Witnesses</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and shewes <hi>them all</hi> that Ever <hi>they</hi> do; the <hi>thoughts,</hi> and the Intents of <hi>their hearts;</hi> and to Deny that <hi>this</hi> is <hi>Truth,</hi> which is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in <hi>them;</hi> and to hold <hi>this</hi> Truth in <hi>Unrighteousness;</hi> and to say it is not the <hi>Christ;</hi> It is not the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>him</hi> that <hi>Lighteth</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man that <hi>cometh</hi> into the <hi>World;</hi> That it is not able to <hi>save,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100369:10"/> which is able to <hi>shew;</hi> for that which <hi>saves shews,</hi> and that which <hi>shews saves;</hi> and <hi>he</hi> that doth the <hi>One</hi> is the <hi>Other, Christ Jesus,</hi> who came to <hi>save</hi> that which was <hi>lost;</hi> who <hi>shews</hi> what is <hi>lost,</hi> and who hath done it, and what <hi>holds</hi> it, and whither it tends, and gives the <hi>sence</hi> of <hi>these</hi> things; as a <hi>Man</hi> that is <hi>made</hi> sensible by a <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbling Stone,</hi> and a <hi>Rock.</hi> What doth this Argue, but that such are <hi>Dead</hi> in <hi>Trespasses</hi> and <hi>Sins,</hi> and that the <hi>Enemy</hi> hath play'd a <hi>sure</hi> Game with <hi>them,</hi> and made <hi>them</hi> to put <hi>themselves</hi> (so far as lies in <hi>them,</hi> and as in <hi>this</hi> state) Out of a <hi>Capacity Ever</hi> to be <hi>Delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if <hi>Men</hi> never had the <hi>sence</hi> of <hi>these</hi> things, or a <hi>Witness</hi> in <hi>them</hi> that it was <hi>so;</hi> It were <hi>something</hi> Excuseable; (though the <hi>Lord</hi> was not bound to <hi>his</hi> Creature, but as he made <hi>him</hi> Upright, and he sought out <hi>many</hi> Inventions, so <hi>he</hi> should be fill'd with <hi>his</hi> Own Doings, and the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>his</hi> hands should be given <hi>him)</hi> but <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his</hi> makes it the <hi>more</hi> Intollerable, that <hi>such</hi> things as these <hi>are;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd yet <hi>Men</hi> follow that which leads into the <hi>Pit,</hi> knowing it to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o; and hate <hi>him</hi> that Reproveth in the <hi>Gate;</hi> The <hi>Voice</hi> of <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which cryeth <hi>without,</hi> and Uttereth <hi>her</hi> Voice in the <hi>streets;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cryeth in the <hi>chief</hi> place of <hi>Concourse</hi> (Read <hi>me</hi> within) for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere <hi>these</hi> things are to be found; and to that which is <hi>within</hi> is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken) in the <hi>Entring</hi> of the <hi>Gates,</hi> and in the <hi>City</hi> saying, <hi>How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g ye simple Ones will ye Love Simplicity, and the Scorners Delight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Scorning, and fools hate Knowledge. Turn ye at my Reproof; Hear and your Souls shall Live.</hi> I say that <hi>Men</hi> should rise against <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is,</hi> should hate <hi>this,</hi> should be Led into a Hating of <hi>this,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ising against <hi>this,</hi> and be <hi>so</hi> deceived by <hi>their</hi> Enemy, what will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>more</hi> Intollerable in the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord?</hi> what <hi>more</hi> Inexcuse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble? and what <hi>more</hi> Matchless Deceit can there be then <hi>this?</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore</hi> to be Avoided?</p>
            <p>In <hi>Bowells</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> I write <hi>thess</hi> things, and in <hi>tender</hi> Compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, that <hi>Men</hi> may see <hi>their</hi> state, and mind to be <hi>Delivered,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>which</hi> waits to Deliver <hi>them,</hi> and which is set for <hi>that</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ose; that <hi>so</hi> the Day of <hi>their</hi> Calamity may not come upon <hi>them</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nawares; and the <hi>Night</hi> which shall never have End. For, <hi>this</hi> testifie from the <hi>Lord</hi> whose <hi>Word</hi> it is, That <hi>his</hi> Spirit will not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wayes</hi> strive with <hi>Flesh;</hi> with whom <hi>his</hi> Spirit hath <hi>been</hi> long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iving, and upon whom <hi>he</hi> hath long waited; but the Day of <hi>his</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong-suffering will have an <hi>End;</hi> and it is <hi>Drawing near,</hi> yea it is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100369:11"/>
               <hi>very</hi> neer, yea even at the <hi>Very Door;</hi> and then <hi>Men</hi> will know what <hi>they</hi> have been Doing, and what hath <hi>led them,</hi> and in what <hi>State they</hi> are, and whom <hi>they</hi> have resisted, and what <hi>they</hi> have gone <hi>Over,</hi> and at what <hi>they</hi> have risen, and how <hi>they</hi> have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <hi>their</hi> Precious time, and not known in <hi>their</hi> Day the things that Concern <hi>their</hi> Peace: For a <hi>sore</hi> Day is <hi>near,</hi> such a Day as <hi>Never</hi> was; wherein Men shall know in <hi>this</hi> World, what <hi>they</hi> have been Doing, and the <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> whom they have <hi>Rejected</hi> and <hi>Despised,</hi> and <hi>Trampled</hi> upon, and <hi>run</hi> Over, and <hi>resisted,</hi> and would <hi>not</hi> have <hi>him</hi> to Reign Over <hi>them;</hi> and then <hi>Wo</hi> will be <hi>their</hi> Day, and <hi>sad</hi> will be <hi>their</hi> Case for <hi>Ever</hi> and <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>these</hi> things are writ for <hi>Men</hi> to Mind and Consider <hi>ere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be too late, and the <hi>Door</hi> be <hi>shut,</hi> and there be <hi>no</hi> Entering; and the <hi>Word</hi> be gone forth, <hi>He that is Unjust let him be Ʋnjust still; Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he that is Filthy, let him be Filthy still; and he that is Righteous, let him be Righteous still; and he that is Holy, let him be Holy still:</hi> For the time is at hand, <hi>And behold I come quickly, and my Reward i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with me, to give every Man as his Work shall be,</hi> saith the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore People <hi>all</hi> be Ye <hi>all</hi> Warned, and <hi>Mind;</hi> whilst <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Long-suffering waits upon <hi>You,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> waits to be <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> lest the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Your</hi> Visitation passing <hi>Over,</hi> it be too late, and with <hi>Prophane</hi> Esau <hi>ye</hi> find <hi>no</hi> Place of <hi>Repentance,</hi> though <hi>Ye</hi> seek it <hi>Carefully</hi> with tears; For <hi>Friends,</hi> this <hi>I know</hi> Certainly from the <hi>Lord,</hi> it is yet but a little time, and <hi>these</hi> things will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e accomplished, and <hi>these</hi> things will be fulfilled, and <hi>Your Ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> shall see it,</hi> the <hi>Eyes</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Generation; and <hi>You</hi> shall remember in <hi>that</hi> Day, that <hi>these</hi> things have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n told <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>Ye</hi> took not Warning, (I speak to such who shall not <hi>take</hi> Warning) and that <hi>they</hi> are now Witnessed upon <hi>You;</hi> and whether <hi>You</hi> will hear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>not,</hi> or Lay it to <hi>heart:</hi> The things are so, <hi>they</hi> are Sealed, <hi>it is Done: He that is Unjust, let him be Unjust still; and he that is Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, let him be Filthy still, and he that is Righteous, let him be Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous still; and he that is Holy, let him be Holy still: And behold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come quickly, and my Reward is with me, to give Every Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Work shall be.</hi> So mind <hi>Ye</hi> all, for the <hi>time</hi> is at <hi>hand,</hi> and <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> shall Witness it. And <hi>these</hi> things am <hi>I</hi> moved of the <hi>Lord G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Almighty, to Write unto <hi>You,</hi> that <hi>Ye</hi> may Know that the <hi>time i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at <hi>hand,</hi> and that it is <hi>Near,</hi> whether <hi>You</hi> will hear, Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>You</hi> will forbear.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100369:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>So Consider</hi> People, and <hi>mind</hi> whilst <hi>Ye</hi> have time, lest the <hi>Night</hi> come upon <hi>You,</hi> and there be an <hi>End;</hi> and <hi>tristle</hi> not away <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> precious Time, lest the <hi>Day</hi> of Sorrow come upon <hi>you,</hi> of which <hi>you</hi> will know no <hi>End:</hi> It's <hi>Love</hi> that speaks to <hi>You;</hi> It's the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> that <hi>Moves</hi> to <hi>you;</hi> It's that which will <hi>laugh</hi> at <hi>your</hi> Calamity, and <hi>Mock</hi> when <hi>your</hi> fear cometh; who will not hear when <hi>Long-suffering</hi> is at an <hi>End,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> will not have Mercy; though <hi>you</hi> may mock at it <hi>now,</hi> and make a <hi>Jest</hi> at it, <hi>is Lot's</hi> Sons in <hi>Law</hi> did, when <hi>he</hi> told them what was coming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>City,</hi> which <hi>he</hi> had received from the <hi>Angels,</hi> he seemed to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as One that <hi>Mocked;</hi> yet the <hi>Fire</hi> came, and they were <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> who <hi>Mocked:</hi> And, <hi>as it was in the Dayes of</hi> Lot, <hi>they did E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, they Drank, they Bought, they Sold, they Planted, they Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; but the same Day that</hi> Lot <hi>went Out of</hi> Sodom, <hi>it rained Fire and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stone from Heaven, and Destroyed them all: Even thus it shall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Day when the Son of Man is Revealed: And as it was in the Dayes of</hi> Noah, <hi>so shall it be also in the Dayes of the Son of Man; They did Eat, they Drank, they Married Wives, they were given in Marriage, until the Day that</hi> Noah <hi>Entered into the Ark, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd came and Destroyed them all.</hi> And this <hi>I</hi> have <hi>certainly</hi> Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed from <hi>God,</hi> that so it will be in the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> and so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> come, and so will <hi>Men</hi> be in the <hi>Day</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Lord,</hi> which will come upon <hi>them as a Thief in the Night; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d when they shall say Peace and Safety, then sudden Destruction co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h upon them, as Travail upon a Woman with Child, and they shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Escape.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Tremble</hi> all before the <hi>Lord God</hi> of <hi>Hosts,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd give <hi>Glory</hi> to <hi>him, for the hour of his</hi> Judgments <hi>is come,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all be revealed upon the <hi>Workers</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> when the <hi>Day</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Visitation is <hi>Over,</hi> and the <hi>Measure</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Iniquity is <hi>up;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the <hi>Lord</hi> hath stayed and waited <hi>long,</hi> and sent <hi>Warning</hi> upon <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ning,</hi> and <hi>Visitation</hi> upon <hi>Visitation,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Witness hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een reacht in <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>you</hi> know <hi>Ye</hi> should not do the <hi>things</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich are done by <hi>You,</hi> and yet <hi>ye</hi> will do <hi>them:</hi> Now what can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>more,</hi> and what can the <hi>Lord</hi> do <hi>more</hi> for <hi>you,</hi> than to reach <hi>his</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itness in <hi>you,</hi> and to quicken <hi>that</hi> which testifies to <hi>him,</hi> so that Answers unto <hi>him,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> should not <hi>do</hi> so and so, and that <hi>ye</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uld do according as <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> witnesseth in <hi>you,</hi> and yet <hi>you</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill do <hi>so</hi> and <hi>so.</hi> Now <hi>More</hi> cannot be done for <hi>you,</hi> than to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100369:12"/> bring <hi>You</hi> to the <hi>Path</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> to <hi>that</hi> which will direct <hi>You</hi> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will <hi>heed</hi> it, and bring <hi>You</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>him</hi> who is the <hi>Savi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> of the <hi>Soul;</hi> which shews <hi>ye</hi> all <hi>your</hi> goings astray, and how <hi>ye</hi> are as <hi>lost</hi> sheep, and how the <hi>Enemy</hi> hath <hi>You,</hi> and leads <hi>You,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what <hi>he</hi> leads <hi>You</hi> into, and what will be the <hi>End</hi> of those things▪ and that the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>those</hi> things is <hi>Death;</hi> and that the <hi>Judgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>God</hi> upon <hi>such</hi> as do <hi>those</hi> things are <hi>Just,</hi> and will leave <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> without Excuse. If <hi>You</hi> will not hearken to <hi>this,</hi> if <hi>You</hi> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be Guided by <hi>this;</hi> if <hi>You</hi> will not <hi>give</hi> up to be ruled by this▪ There is <hi>never</hi> another way to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> ye must <hi>Die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> your</hi> Sins, ye must <hi>Perish</hi> Everlastingly.</p>
            <p>So the <hi>Bowells</hi> of <hi>my</hi> Love are moved to <hi>You,</hi> and for <hi>You,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>You</hi> may know in <hi>this</hi> your Day the <hi>things</hi> that belong to y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Peace, <hi>Ere</hi> they be <hi>hid</hi> from <hi>your</hi> Eyes; for this <hi>I</hi> testifie unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whose <hi>Word</hi> I say again it is, and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> what I say: That when <hi>Once</hi> the <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Visitation is <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>your Day</hi> closed up; <hi>You</hi> will not believe <hi>though One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the Dead: I</hi> say Again, and <hi>Mind</hi> what <hi>I say, you will not belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> though One arise from the Dead.</hi> For then the <hi>time</hi> of <hi>Repent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will be <hi>Over your</hi> heads; And <hi>Iniquity</hi> being got Over the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and having Covered the <hi>Witness,</hi> that wherein is the <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and having filled <hi>You</hi> up, that will not <hi>hear,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> You</hi> to <hi>hear;</hi> for it hath got the <hi>start</hi> upon <hi>You,</hi> and run <hi>ye</hi> Ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Floud</hi> is <hi>Come,</hi> and will <hi>sweep</hi> ye away.</p>
            <p>So in <hi>Bowells</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> I still speak unto <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> could Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>beseech you; I</hi> could Even come upon <hi>my</hi> Knee (as it were) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and for <hi>you</hi> all, that <hi>ye</hi> would receive <hi>him</hi> who speaks from <hi>Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that <hi>ye</hi> would be Reconciled to <hi>God,</hi> who is in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrist Jesus re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciling the World unto himself; and not imputing unto them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Transgressions;</hi> who turn to <hi>him,</hi> to <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> that calls up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>them,</hi> that shews <hi>them</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> that stands in <hi>their</hi> Way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them to God; which is laid by the Lord in the Way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Men</hi> to him. In <hi>Sion,</hi> in <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> which answers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>him;</hi> Witnesses for <hi>him;</hi> for <hi>other</hi> where it is not laid; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> when this is <hi>Covered</hi> Over which witnesses to <hi>him,</hi> and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not <hi>heard;</hi> then that which is laid in the <hi>Way</hi> will not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found; for it is laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> in that of <hi>him</hi> till it arise in <hi>yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Worm</hi> that will <hi>never</hi> Die, and a <hi>Fire</hi> that will <hi>never</hi> go out; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then it will be <hi>sad</hi> for <hi>you,</hi> when that shall <hi>Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you</hi> which <hi>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100369:12"/>
               <hi>You;</hi> and that shall Condemn <hi>You</hi> which would have shewn <hi>ye</hi> Mercy; and that <hi>Live</hi> in <hi>You</hi> an <hi>Everlasting</hi> Punishment, which would have been to <hi>You Life</hi> Eternal.</p>
            <p>For <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>thing,</hi> if <hi>ye</hi> desire to know it, and the <hi>Sum</hi> of the <hi>Matter.</hi> If <hi>that</hi> Live not in <hi>You,</hi> which moves <hi>You</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and shews <hi>ye</hi> Evil; and if <hi>You</hi> live not <hi>in</hi> it, and be guided <hi>by</hi> it, It will <hi>live</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> a <hi>Punishment</hi> for <hi>Evil;</hi> and that from <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Ever</hi> and <hi>Ever.</hi> And when the <hi>Measure</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Iniquity is filled up, <hi>You</hi> will know it. But <hi>I</hi> would <hi>ye</hi> knew it before, that is, whilst the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Long-suffering</hi> is, <hi>I</hi> would, and it is the <hi>Desire</hi> of <hi>my</hi> Soul, and <hi>I</hi> am <hi>moved</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whose <hi>Bowells</hi> in <hi>me</hi> are to <hi>You</hi> wards, that <hi>ye</hi> knew <hi>that that</hi> witnesseth, and that <hi>ye</hi> would be gathered unto <hi>it,</hi> before the <hi>Decree bring</hi> forth; For, when the <hi>Day</hi> is <hi>Over, Iniquity</hi> will fill <hi>ye</hi> up, and it will be <hi>too</hi> late; there will be <hi>no</hi> place to <hi>hear,</hi> the <hi>place</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> will not be <hi>found,</hi> for it is in <hi>that</hi> which answereth to <hi>God;</hi> which <hi>Iniquity</hi> hath <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</hi> Over, and <hi>so</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> strives <hi>no</hi> More, nor are <hi>his</hi> Arms <hi>stretched</hi> out to <hi>gather</hi> You; but the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> will rule in <hi>You;</hi> and the <hi>Cart-Ropes</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> will draw <hi>You:</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e who hath filled <hi>You,</hi> will lead <hi>You</hi> forth against <hi>that which</hi> hath Visited <hi>You,</hi> and against <hi>them in</hi> whom <hi>it</hi> lives; and <hi>You</hi> will do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things against <hi>that</hi> Name, by which <hi>ye</hi> might have been saved, and which waited to save <hi>You,</hi> but <hi>ye</hi> would not. Then <hi>that</hi> which <hi>Visited You,</hi> will suffer by <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> those in whom it <hi>is,</hi> will come to suffer by <hi>You;</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> which hath <hi>Murdered</hi> the <hi>Just</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> will carry <hi>ye</hi> out to <hi>Murder them</hi> in whom is the <hi>Just,</hi> and to try <hi>them,</hi> and to make <hi>them</hi> pass <hi>through Deep</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, whom the <hi>Lord</hi> will Uphold by the <hi>Right hand</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Power, to Endure <hi>that</hi> which <hi>he</hi> shall suffer that Spirit by <hi>You</hi> to bring upon <hi>them;</hi> as a <hi>Testimony</hi> unto <hi>them,</hi> and unto <hi>You,</hi> that <hi>God is</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> and that ye are of the <hi>Devil,</hi> till ye have done <hi>your Work,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> sees it is enough; and stops <hi>your</hi> hand, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mbles <hi>You</hi> into the <hi>Pit;</hi> with that which hath led <hi>ye</hi> forth, there to be tormented with it for <hi>Ever,</hi> and <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, <hi>this</hi> let <hi>me</hi> tell <hi>You,</hi> and it may <hi>be</hi> as a <hi>Sign</hi> unto <hi>You;</hi> That when <hi>ye</hi> are let <hi>loose</hi> to Do what is Determined upon the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for <hi>You</hi> to Do, which the <hi>Witness</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet keeps <hi>ye</hi> from, and <hi>ye</hi> cannot yet <hi>get</hi> Over, because of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at in <hi>You,</hi> which <hi>Witnesses</hi> for <hi>them;</hi> and so the <hi>Long-Suffering</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>God</hi> yet <hi>waiteth;</hi> then <hi>your</hi> Day is at an <hi>End,</hi> and the <hi>hour</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100369:13"/>
               <hi>your</hi> Visitation is <hi>Over,</hi> and you are <hi>filling</hi> up <hi>your</hi> measure for <hi>your</hi> Destruction.</p>
            <p>Therefore, heed whilst <hi>ye</hi> have time, for <hi>assuredly</hi> as <hi>You</hi> shall do <hi>those</hi> things, shall the <hi>Day</hi> come upon <hi>You;</hi> and <hi>assuredly</hi> as <hi>those</hi> things are done, is <hi>your</hi> Day Over; and this <hi>You</hi> shall Witness to <hi>me</hi> Every <hi>One</hi> that is found <hi>here</hi> in the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord:</hi> Therefore <hi>Consider</hi> and be <hi>Wise,</hi> and <hi>rush</hi> not <hi>headlong</hi> into <hi>Destruction;</hi> For the <hi>Lord</hi> will enable <hi>his</hi> People to endure, that in <hi>them</hi> which is of <hi>him</hi> shall <hi>live</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> Do <hi>ye</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> can, &amp; carry <hi>them</hi> through all <hi>ye</hi> shall be <hi>suffered</hi> to do unto <hi>them;</hi> And shall <hi>arise</hi> as <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> and Execute upon <hi>You</hi> the <hi>Judgement</hi> that is written, <hi>This Honour have all his Saints;</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> for <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> and give <hi>Glory</hi> unto <hi>him</hi> (I say again in the <hi>Movings</hi> of the <hi>Lord)</hi> and <hi>heed</hi> that which is laid in <hi>your</hi> Way to <hi>stumble</hi> at, to <hi>offend You,</hi> to turn <hi>ye</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> and be <hi>no</hi> longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by <hi>your</hi> Enemy, who seeks <hi>your</hi> hurt; for as it is said to <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> before, It's the <hi>greatest</hi> Deceit that can be <hi>Imaginable,</hi> for <hi>any</hi> so to be Deceived, as to rise up against <hi>that,</hi> and hate <hi>that,</hi> which is <hi>set</hi> to Deliver <hi>it,</hi> and without which <hi>it</hi> cannot he <hi>Delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Instance;</hi> If a <hi>Man</hi> should be fallen into a <hi>Desper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Lethargie; Or, <hi>any</hi> other Mortal Disease, out of, or from which it is <hi>Impossible</hi> for <hi>him</hi> to escape without the <hi>help</hi> of <hi>such</hi> a <hi>One</hi> as is set before <hi>him.</hi> If the <hi>so Diseased</hi> Man shall be raised up again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>this</hi> Physitian, with <hi>such</hi> Prejudice that <hi>he</hi> accounts the Physitian, as <hi>his</hi> Mortal Enemy, and <hi>stumbles</hi> at whatsoever <hi>he</hi> Prescribes unto <hi>him,</hi> and is offended <hi>thereat;</hi> This Man <hi>certainly</hi> in the estimation of <hi>all</hi> according unto <hi>Men,</hi> must miscarry, and will be accounted by <hi>all</hi> to be the <hi>most</hi> grievously deceived; and cannot be thought <hi>point blank</hi> to be <hi>more</hi> mistaken, nor <hi>more</hi> desperately, then in <hi>such</hi> a Point as this.</p>
            <p>And yet (as <hi>I</hi> have shewed) This is the <hi>Case</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Men, who <hi>stumble</hi> at the <hi>Stumbling-Stone,</hi> and are offended at the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence;</hi> at that which is the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> to as <hi>many</hi> as believe and are carryed out against <hi>this. Their</hi> Case is <hi>Desperate;</hi> and <hi>No</hi> Mens More, and <hi>No</hi> Men can be <hi>more</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; Nor can a <hi>Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> lead <hi>more</hi> misterious and <hi>Damnable,</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which leads unto <hi>this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then is of <hi>great</hi> Weight, and worthy the <hi>while well</hi> to lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into, and <hi>Maturely</hi> to consider, how <hi>Man</hi> came at <hi>first</hi> to be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> deceived, and <hi>thus</hi> to be led against <hi>that</hi> which came, and is <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100369:13"/> to deliver <hi>him,</hi> by the <hi>Enemy</hi> who seeks to des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roy <hi>him,</hi> and hath <hi>him</hi> in <hi>subjection;</hi> and how it comes to <hi>pass,</hi> that the <hi>Experience</hi> of <hi>this</hi> sore hurt through <hi>all</hi> Ages, hath not yet so Awakened the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erallity</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> and opened <hi>their</hi> Eyes, so as to see <hi>their</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and <hi>his</hi> deceit, and to be <hi>turned</hi> to the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Order hereunto, <hi>I</hi> shall shew <hi>how</hi> Man came into the <hi>fall,</hi> and <hi>how</hi> he is <hi>held</hi> under it by <hi>him</hi> who hath <hi>him</hi> under, and against <hi>him</hi> who is come to deliver <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> thus came into the <hi>fall;</hi> It was not by <hi>strength</hi> of <hi>Art,</hi> nor by <hi>Sophistication</hi> of the <hi>Enemy, so</hi> much as by <hi>his</hi> Letting in the <hi>Enemy,</hi> when <hi>he</hi> sought to deceive <hi>him,</hi> when <hi>he</hi> hearkned to, and Parlied with <hi>him,</hi> and received <hi>his</hi> Suggestions into <hi>his</hi> Mind as <hi>Matter</hi> to <hi>Consider;</hi> When <hi>he</hi> gave <hi>it</hi> place by <hi>Consideration,</hi> and <hi>so</hi> Opened the <hi>Door,</hi> then the <hi>Enemy</hi> entred, and being in, then <hi>he</hi> wrought for <hi>himself:</hi> and that of <hi>him</hi> being entred, It became <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Man,</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> the <hi>Eye,</hi> the <hi>Ear,</hi> the <hi>Hand,</hi> the <hi>Foot,</hi> by which <hi>he</hi> saw, <hi>heard, acted,</hi> and <hi>went</hi> to <hi>Every</hi> thing, <hi>Unsuspected</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi> because <hi>Man</hi> had let it <hi>in</hi> as that which <hi>was</hi> good, and had prostrated <hi>all</hi> he had unto <hi>It.</hi> So the <hi>Enemy</hi> got into a <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise,</hi> and put <hi>himself</hi> into a <hi>shape</hi> to Enter, and having <hi>Entred, This</hi> Disguise, <hi>this</hi> shape fashioned <hi>Man</hi> into <hi>its</hi> Image, and made <hi>him</hi> like unto it; who was made <hi>after the Image of God,</hi> and was like <hi>God,</hi> whilst <hi>he</hi> stood in <hi>that</hi> state, and that of <hi>God</hi> acted in <hi>him,</hi> and was <hi>his</hi> Eye, <hi>his</hi> Ear, <hi>his</hi> Hand, and <hi>his</hi> Foot, and <hi>Did</hi> all for <hi>him;</hi> or whilst <hi>all</hi> that <hi>he</hi> did, <hi>saw, heard,</hi> or <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> was by <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> Or, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>him;</hi> Or, the <hi>Soul</hi> that <hi>he</hi> had made; Or, the <hi>breath</hi> which <hi>he</hi> had breathed into <hi>him. And the Lord breathed into Man the Breath of Life, and Man became a Living Soul; after the Image of God Created <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him, in Righteousness and true Holiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>here</hi> lay <hi>Man's</hi> hurt at <hi>first,</hi> and <hi>here</hi> the <hi>hurt</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Men lies at <hi>this</hi> Day, who are in <hi>that</hi> state; In that <hi>he</hi> hearkned to the <hi>Enemy,</hi> received <hi>him,</hi> Let <hi>him</hi> in; not <hi>so</hi> much that the <hi>Enemy</hi> came to deceive <hi>him;</hi> For, <hi>his</hi> coming to deceive <hi>him</hi> had signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>little,</hi> if <hi>Man</hi> had kept <hi>Entire</hi> to <hi>that</hi> in <hi>him</hi> in which <hi>he</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de, which <hi>was</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which would have shewed <hi>him his</hi> Enemy, and have kept <hi>him</hi> out. For, whilst his <hi>Eye</hi> was Single, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>he</hi> kept there, it was <hi>Impossible</hi> that he should have been <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d;</hi> because the <hi>Eye</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>him</hi> could have <hi>No</hi> fellowship
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100369:14"/> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the <hi>Enemy,</hi> Nor admit in, Upon <hi>any</hi> Account; nor <hi>savour,</hi> nor <hi>accept</hi> him, for <hi>its</hi> Nature is contrary; But <hi>Man</hi> letting in the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and giving <hi>his</hi> Consent, that which <hi>he</hi> let in became <hi>his</hi> Eye, and so Darkned <hi>him</hi> as to the <hi>Eye</hi> of God; which <hi>saw,</hi> and discovered, and which it <hi>put</hi> out; Or, <hi>brought</hi> under. And so <hi>his</hi> foolish heart became <hi>Darkned,</hi> and saw <hi>nothing</hi> but according unto that which <hi>put</hi> it under.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And when the Woman saw, that the Tree was good for food, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it was pleasant to the Eyes, and a Tree to be desired to make One Wise,</hi> (here the <hi>Enemy</hi> got <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>she</hi> saw with <hi>his</hi> Eye) <hi>she took of the Fruit thereof,</hi> (when <hi>Lust</hi> hath conceived it <hi>bringeth</hi> forth <hi>Sin;</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> when it is <hi>finished bringeth</hi> forth <hi>Death) and did Eat</hi> (here <hi>she</hi> Joyned with the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> twain became <hi>One</hi> Flesh) <hi>and she gave also to her husband with her, and he did Eat</hi> (here <hi>they</hi> became the <hi>betrayers of One</hi> Another into the <hi>same</hi> Perdition.)</p>
            <p>Now <hi>she</hi> had <hi>let</hi> in the <hi>Serpent,</hi> Who had said unto <hi>her; Yea, hath God said ye shall not Eat of Every Tree of the Garden? And the Woman said unto the Serpent, we may Eat of the Fruit of the Trees i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Garden, but of the Fruit of the Tree, which is in the midst of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Garden; God hath said, ye shall not Eat of it; Neither shall ye t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it lest ye Die. And the Serpent said unto the Woman, ye shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> surely Die, for God doth know that in the Day that ye Eat thereof, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Eyes shall be Opened, and ye shall be as Gods, knowing Good, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Evil. And when the Woman saw that the Tree was Good for Fool, and pleasant to the Eye, and a Tree to be desired to make One Wise,</hi> (see how the <hi>Enemy</hi> now lookt through the <hi>Woman</hi> into whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was got, and how <hi>he Judged</hi> in <hi>her;</hi> and how <hi>her</hi> Judgement w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> according to <hi>his,</hi> who was got in her, the Ground of <hi>her</hi> miscarriage as hath been <hi>said) she took of the Fruit thereof,</hi> (as aforesaid) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> did Eat, and gave it also to her Husband with her, and he did E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>▪</hi> And <hi>so</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> beguiled <hi>her</hi> entring into <hi>her; he</hi> being entred▪ <hi>she</hi> saw with <hi>his Eye,</hi> who before saw with the <hi>Eye</hi> of God: <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath said ye shall not Eat of it; Neither shall ye touch it lest ye D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> This spake that of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>her;</hi> here if <hi>she</hi> had <hi>abided she</hi> had <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> well; had <hi>she</hi> stood in the <hi>state</hi> in which <hi>she</hi> was made, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Holiness,</hi> and <hi>Righteousness,</hi> but <hi>she</hi> went from <hi>this,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>contrary; Yea, hath God said ye shall not Eat of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Tree in the Garden: Ye shall not surely Die, for God doth know t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Day that ye Eat thereof, then your Eyes shall be Opened, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100369:14"/>
               <hi>shall be as Gods, knowing both Good and Evil.</hi> So this <hi>she</hi> let in; and <hi>this</hi> being got <hi>in</hi> with this <hi>she</hi> saw as did <hi>also her</hi> hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; to wit, with <hi>that</hi> which was <hi>got</hi> in to <hi>her,</hi> and <hi>she</hi> had Let in; the <hi>Eye</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> which was <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> And <hi>here</hi> came the <hi>fall,</hi> and here is the <hi>true</hi> state of <hi>Every</hi> Man in the <hi>fall,</hi> be <hi>his</hi> particular Condition <hi>more</hi> or <hi>less; That</hi> which is <hi>the</hi> hurt, is <hi>that</hi> which Leads aside; <hi>that which</hi> deceives, <hi>that which</hi> makes to miscarry, is not <hi>so</hi> much <hi>that which</hi> comes <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> and <hi>presents,</hi> and <hi>Tempts,</hi> but <hi>that which</hi> Enters; <hi>which</hi> takes a place in <hi>Man,</hi> being Enrred; <hi>which</hi> begets <hi>something</hi> of <hi>its</hi> Own; <hi>which</hi> being begotten, <hi>growes</hi> up in <hi>Man</hi> in which <hi>he</hi> is, and with which <hi>Man</hi> sees, and <hi>feels,</hi> and <hi>Understands,</hi> which is <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>so</hi> becomes the <hi>Child</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> a <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>Wrath.</hi> Whereas, were not the <hi>Enemy</hi> suffered to <hi>Enter;</hi> or did <hi>he</hi> not lodge <hi>within;</hi> that of <hi>God</hi> which is <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> would <hi>guide</hi> and <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here is the <hi>great</hi> Mystery of <hi>Ungodliness;</hi> being Entred it <hi>beguiles</hi> the <hi>Understanding,</hi> and <hi>puts</hi> it into <hi>mistakes,</hi> and makes it to think that <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> which is <hi>quite</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and so the <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>God</hi> comes upon <hi>Man,</hi> because that hath possessed <hi>him,</hi> and leads <hi>him,</hi> and hath <hi>his</hi> Ear and <hi>his</hi> Heart which is <hi>Contrary</hi> to <hi>God:</hi> And <hi>so</hi> nothing <hi>that he</hi> doth, pleaseth <hi>God,</hi> being in the <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Possessed,</hi> or <hi>Led,</hi> or <hi>guided</hi> by <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>Emnity</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> that <hi>neither</hi> sees <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>knows</hi> him; but doth the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>him</hi> of <hi>whom</hi> it <hi>is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>here</hi> is the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>all Men</hi> by <hi>Nature;</hi> The <hi>Nature</hi> that is in the <hi>Transgression, Children</hi> of <hi>Wrath, Children</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by him, the <hi>Spirit</hi> that is in <hi>them</hi> that <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Guides</hi> them. I do not say, that <hi>Man</hi> as a <hi>Creature</hi> in the <hi>state,</hi> wherein <hi>he</hi> was made, is the <hi>begotten</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> or, the <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>him;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Man Upright,</hi> and <hi>after the Image of God made he him, in Righteousness, and true Holiness;</hi> and <hi>he was</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and proceeded from <hi>him;</hi> But the <hi>Devil</hi> Entring into <hi>Man;</hi> Or, <hi>Man</hi> suffering, or <hi>Letting</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> to Enter into <hi>him;</hi> who might have kept <hi>him</hi> out, and was made in <hi>that</hi> state that the <hi>Devil</hi> had no <hi>Part</hi> in <hi>him;</hi> Nor could have forced <hi>him;</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> begot <hi>his</hi> Own Image in <hi>him;</hi> a <hi>Spirit</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> which <hi>Leads</hi> him to <hi>do,</hi> and which <hi>doth</hi> the <hi>works</hi> of the <hi>Devil naturally,</hi> as a <hi>Child</hi> the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>him</hi> that begat <hi>him;</hi> and of that <hi>Spirit</hi> that ruleth in <hi>him.</hi> Something is <hi>begotten</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> which rules <hi>him;</hi> which hath <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100369:15"/> with the <hi>Devil,</hi> that is <hi>Joyned</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> that is <hi>become</hi> One Flesh; that doth <hi>all</hi> his works <hi>in him;</hi> that doth <hi>his</hi> works; that is, of <hi>his</hi> Root and <hi>Generation</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>Curst,</hi> and who is in the <hi>Alienation</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> and neither sees <hi>him;</hi> Nor can know <hi>him.</hi> So <hi>his Children ye are whose works ye do;</hi> And <hi>I speak that which I have seen with my Father, and ye do that which ye have seen with your Father</hi> (saith <hi>Christ</hi> to the <hi>Pharisees)</hi> And <hi>his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ye are to whom ye Obey; and whosoever committeth Sin is the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Sin;</hi> And <hi>if ye were Abrahams Children, ye would do the Works of Abraham. But now ye seek to kill me; A Man that hath told ye the Truth which I have heard of God, this did not Abraham. Ye do the Deeds of your Father, Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the Lusts of your Father ye will do; he was a Murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and ahode not in the Truth; because there is no Truth in him: when he speaketh a Lie, he speaketh of his Own; for he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lyar and the Father of it,</hi> John 8. 34, 38, 39, 40, 44. Rom. 6. 16. And <hi>whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither known him; He that committeth Sin is of the Devil, for the Devil sinneth from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; in this the Children of God are manifest, and the Children of the Devil; Whosoever doth not Righteousness is not of God; Neither he that loveth not his Brother,</hi> 1 John 3. 6, 8, 10. And in <hi>this</hi> state <hi>Every</hi> Man is <hi>accursed</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and cannot <hi>come near</hi> him; for <hi>he</hi> is a <hi>God of Purer Eyes then to behold Evil; nor can he look on Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> Habbuk. 1. 13. He is not a <hi>God that hath pleasure in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, neither shall Evil dwell with him,</hi> Psal. 5. 4. And <hi>there shall in no wise enter into it, any thing that defileth; neither whatsoever worketh Abomination, Or maketh a Lie; but they which are written in the Lambs Book of Life,</hi> Revel. 21. 27. And <hi>without are Doggs, and Sorcerers,</hi> and <hi>Whore-Mongers,</hi> and <hi>Murderers,</hi> and <hi>Idolaters, and whosoever Loveth, and maketh a Lie,</hi> Revel. 22. 15. And the reason is because of that which is begotten in <hi>him,</hi> which is in <hi>Emnity</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> which <hi>leads</hi> Man into the <hi>same.</hi> And <hi>here</hi> Man comes to be <hi>Cut</hi> off from <hi>God</hi> his Maker, and to have <hi>no</hi> Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with <hi>him;</hi> but to have <hi>his</hi> Portion with <hi>him</hi> whom <hi>he</hi> serves, in the <hi>Lake</hi> that burneth with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimstone,</hi> which is the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> Death.</p>
            <p>Now to <hi>save</hi> Man, and to <hi>Deliver</hi> him from <hi>this</hi> State, in which <hi>he</hi> is thus by <hi>Nature,</hi> and from <hi>Wrath</hi> to <hi>Come;</hi> and to bring <hi>him</hi> into the <hi>State</hi> in which <hi>he</hi> was before; the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid a <hi>Stone,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100369:15"/> a <hi>Rock,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> in <hi>Sion,</hi> (in <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him)</hi> which is in <hi>Every</hi> Man, which is <hi>under)</hi> to guid <hi>him</hi> into the <hi>Way</hi> again; and <hi>this Rock</hi> is <hi>Christ.—They Drank of the Spiritual Rock which followed them, and that Rock was Christ—</hi>Said <hi>Paul</hi> of the <hi>Israelites</hi> in the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 4. And saith <hi>Old</hi> Jacob of <hi>Joseph, Joseph is a fruitful Bough, Even a fruitful Bough by a Well; The Archers have s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly grieved him, and shot at him, and hated him, but his Bow abod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in strength; and the Arms of his hands were made strong by the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ds of the Mighty God of</hi> Jacob; <hi>from thence is the Shepherd, the STONE of Israel,</hi> Gen. 49. 22, 23, 24. And, <hi>behold I lay in Sion for a Foundation, a STONE, a tryed STONE, a Precious Corner STONE, a sure Foundation, he that believeth shall not make haste▪ Judgment also will I lay to the Line, and Righteousness to the Plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>; and the Hail shall sweep away the Refuge of Lies, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters shall Overflow the Hiding-place; and your Covenant with Death shall be Disanulled, and your Agreement with Hell shall not stand; when the Overflowing Scourge shall pass thorow, then Ye shall be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down by it. From the time that it goeth forth it shall take you; for Morning by Morning shall it pass Over, by Day, and by Night, and it shall be a Vexation only to understand the Report. For the Bed is shorter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that a Man can stretch himself on it, and the Covering Narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n that he can wrap himself in it. For the Lord shall rise up as in Mount</hi> Perazim, <hi>he shall be Wroth as in the Valley of</hi> Gibeon; <hi>that he may do his Work, his strange Work, and bring to pass his Act, his strange Act. Now therefore be Ye not Mockers, lest your Bands be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> strong: for I have heard from the Lord of Hosts a Consumption, Even Determined upon the whole Earth,</hi> Isa. 28. 16, to the 23. That which followed <hi>them,</hi> which shewed <hi>them their</hi> Way, which brought <hi>them</hi> out of <hi>Egrpt,</hi> which gave <hi>them Water</hi> in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> that was the <hi>Rock,</hi> that the <hi>Shepheard,</hi> the <hi>STONE</hi> of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>they</hi> rebelled against the <hi>Lord,</hi> and made them a <hi>Malten</hi> Calf, and <hi>Murmurred</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> and <hi>Committed Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with the <hi>Daughters</hi> of <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Worshipped</hi> their Gods, the <hi>Gods</hi> of <hi>them</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whom the <hi>Lord</hi> had Cast out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fore <hi>them:</hi> And as for <hi>this</hi> Man <hi>Moses,</hi> they would not have <hi>him</hi> to Rule Over <hi>them;</hi> and who made <hi>thee a Ruler and a Judge Over Ʋs?</hi> Said <hi>he</hi> that Wronged his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> to <hi>Moses, Wilt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> kill me as thou didst the</hi> Egyptian <hi>yesterday?</hi> When <hi>Moses shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100369:16"/>
               <hi>himself to them as they strove, and would have set them at One again,</hi> and said unto them, <hi>Sirs, Ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong One a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother?</hi> And <hi>ye have killed the People of the Lord.</hi> Said they that Rebelled to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> concerning <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> Company, the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Congregation</hi> who rose up <hi>against Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> whom the <hi>Earth</hi> opened her <hi>Mouth</hi> upon, and <hi>swallowed</hi> them up; because the <hi>Earth</hi> opened <hi>her Mouth</hi> and <hi>swallowed</hi> them up, and the <hi>fire</hi> of the Lord consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>them:</hi> Who said to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Ye take too much upon You, seeing all the Congregation are holy Every One of them, and the Lord is among them; Wherefore then, lift ye up your selves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> And <hi>Moses</hi> said, <hi>Even to morrow will the Lord shew who are his, and who is holy, and will cause him to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> near unto him; Even him whom he hath chosen, will he cause to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e near unto him; and the Lord did so,</hi> Numb. 16. And <hi>they</hi> thrust <hi>him</hi> from <hi>them.</hi> And therefore <hi>Steven,</hi> when <hi>he</hi> spake to the <hi>Chief Priests,</hi> and the <hi>Council,</hi> when <hi>they</hi> had <hi>him</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> before <hi>them,</hi> said, <hi>This</hi> Moses <hi>whom they refused, saying, Who made thee</hi> a <hi>Ruler</hi> and a <hi>Judge? The same did God send to be a Ruler and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer by the hands of the Angel, which appeared to him in the Bush; For he supposed his Brethren would have understood, how that God by his hand would have delivered them, but they understood not,</hi> Acts 7. 25, 26, 27, 28, 35. He brought <hi>them</hi> out, (whom <hi>they</hi> thus refused, and thrust thus away, and said so to, and <hi>he</hi> was forced to <hi>flie,</hi> vers. 29.) after <hi>he</hi> had shewed <hi>Wonders</hi> and <hi>Signs</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and in the <hi>Wilderness</hi> Forty Years; <hi>This is that Moses</hi> (said he) <hi>which said unto the Children of Israel, A Prophet shall the Lord your God raise up unto You, of your Brethren, like unto Me, him shall you hear: This is he that was in the Church in the Wilderness, with the Angel which spoke to him in the Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and with Our Fathers, who received the lively Oracles to give unto Us; To whom Our Fathers would not Obey, but</hi> [Thurst] <hi>him from them; and in their hearts turned back again into</hi> Egypt, <hi>say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto</hi> Aaron, <hi>Make Ʋs Gods to go before Us, for as for this</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses <hi>which brought Us out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>We wot not what is become of him: And they made a Calf in those Dayes, and offered Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto the Idol, and rejoyced in the Works of their Own hands. Then God turned, and gave them up to Worship the Host of Heaven; As it is written in the Book of the Prophets. O ye house of Israel, have Ye offered unto me slain Beasts, and Sacrifices, by the space of</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100369:16"/>
               <hi>forty years in the Wilderness?</hi> Yea, <hi>ye took up the Tabernacle of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Star of your God Rempham, Figures which ye made to Worship them; and I will carry ye away beyond Babylon,</hi> vers. 36. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e 44. Thus was it with <hi>Israel</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Wilderness;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>this</hi> was the <hi>stumbling;</hi> at this the <hi>Offence;</hi> and at this <hi>they</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mbled; with <hi>this</hi> they were <hi>offended; Him</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> had sent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o deliver <hi>them;</hi> and by <hi>whose</hi> hand <hi>he</hi> did deliver <hi>them.</hi> And One would think, <hi>this</hi> were strange considering the <hi>Bondage</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich <hi>they</hi> were, and the <hi>Mighty</hi> Signs <hi>and Wonders</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> had shewed by the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Moses,</hi> which made the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>fail,</hi> and of the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> whitherto <hi>they</hi> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing to <hi>Possess</hi> by the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Moses;</hi> by whom the <hi>Lord</hi> had <hi>so</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oke unto them, and <hi>all</hi> that Moses had said unto <hi>them</hi> from the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> not <hi>One</hi> word had failed, but <hi>they</hi> had seen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfilled.</p>
            <p>Now what was the <hi>Reason</hi> of this? and how came <hi>this</hi> to Pass? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> because and by reason of the <hi>spirit</hi> that Led <hi>them;</hi> the <hi>spirit</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Egypt</hi> which was got into <hi>them;</hi> which filled <hi>them</hi> with <hi>Egypt;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d made <hi>them</hi> see nothing, nor <hi>think</hi> upon but <hi>Egypt;</hi> So in <hi>their</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts <hi>they</hi> daparted unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> because the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>their</hi> hearts; and that minded nothing but <hi>Egypt,</hi> though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was the place of <hi>their</hi> Servitude; and the Lord after 400. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, according to <hi>his</hi> Promise, Even the <hi>self</hi> same <hi>Day</hi> delivered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out of Egypt, and brought <hi>them</hi> forth with an <hi>Out stretched</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. But it wat <hi>Egypt</hi> that guided, which was <hi>got</hi> in, that held <hi>them</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er <hi>sore</hi> Bondage, not <hi>that</hi> which brought <hi>them</hi> out, and led <hi>them</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rds <hi>Canaan; Egypt</hi> led <hi>them</hi> in <hi>their</hi> hearts back again unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; to <hi>suffer</hi> again; to be in <hi>Bondage</hi> again; who were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed from <hi>Egypt.</hi> The <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> entred in, when the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were <hi>dead</hi> upon the <hi>shoar,</hi> and the <hi>Israelites</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Mighty</hi> works of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Wonders in the <hi>Deep;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>they</hi> sang, when they <hi>saw</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> lying <hi>Dead</hi> upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>And the Waters Covered their Enemies, there was not One of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> left. Then believed they his Words; they sang his Praise. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t his Works; they waited not for his Counsel; but Lusted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dingly in the Wilderness</hi> (here <hi>Egypt</hi> got in) <hi>and tempted God in Desert, and he gave them their request, but sent Leanness into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Soul. They Envyed Moses also in the Camp, and Aaron the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord; The Earth Opened, and Swallowed up Dathan,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100369:17"/>
               <hi>and Covered the Company of Abiram; and a Fire was kindled in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Companies; the Flame burnt up the Wicked. They made a Calf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Horeb; and worshipped the Molten Image. Thus they changed their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the Similitude of an Ox that Eateth Grass. They forgot G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their Saviour, which had done great things in Egypt; Wondrous thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Land of Ham, and terrible things by the Red Sea; Theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he said that he would destroy them; had not Moses his chosen (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they</hi> refused, and <hi>thrust</hi> from <hi>them</hi> and said, <hi>Who made thee a J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Ruler Over Us?)</hi> and <hi>as for this</hi> Moses <hi>we wot not what is be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of him.</hi> For <hi>they</hi> understood not <hi>his</hi> Wonders in <hi>Egypt; they</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred not the <hi>Multitude</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Mercies; <hi>Egypt</hi> that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in, Remembred <hi>them not,</hi> neither <hi>Understood</hi> them which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> filled <hi>them</hi> up; and turned <hi>them</hi> back again in <hi>their</hi> hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Egypt;</hi> but Provoked <hi>him</hi> at the <hi>Sea,</hi> (Even at the <hi>Red Sea) I s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had not <hi>Moses his Chosen,</hi> (whom they <hi>thus</hi> thrust from <hi>them) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Breach, to turn away his Wrath least he should Destroy the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Yea, <hi>they despised the pleasant Land</hi> (those into <hi>whose</hi> hearts <hi>Eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was got: which had turned <hi>them</hi> back in <hi>their</hi> hearts to <hi>Egypt) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> believed not his Word</hi> (who <hi>believed</hi> and <hi>sang</hi> his <hi>Praise)</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> saw the <hi>Egyptians</hi> dead; that which <hi>saw</hi> the Egyptians dead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>it,</hi> but <hi>Egypt,</hi> being got <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> seeing with it, believed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> It was <hi>Egypt,</hi> which could not <hi>believe,</hi> which was the <hi>contrary</hi> that which <hi>believed,</hi> which was <hi>believed,</hi> and its <hi>End</hi> to <hi>lead</hi> ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>it; this</hi> having Possession in <hi>them,</hi> made <hi>them</hi> not to believe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what <hi>work</hi> a <hi>wrong</hi> spirit makes when once it is Entred; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> contrary it leads, and how it makes <hi>those</hi> in whom it <hi>is</hi> as <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and not the <hi>same:</hi> for then that <hi>spirit</hi> hath Dominion, for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot enter, whilst the <hi>Contrary</hi> unto it hath the <hi>rule;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the reason why <hi>Men</hi> are <hi>so</hi> Contrary, and as if <hi>they</hi> were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>same;</hi> because of the <hi>spirit</hi> that is got in <hi>them,</hi> and hath the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which is quite <hi>Contrary,</hi> and bringeth forth the <hi>Contrary</hi> Effe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> So <hi>trust ye not in a Friend; Put ye not Confidence in a Guide; K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Doors of thy Mouth from her that lies in thy Bosome.</hi> For, <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dishonoureth the Father; the Daughter rises up against her Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Daughter in Law against her Mother in Law; A Man's Ene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are the Men of his Own house: Therefore, I will look unto the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I will wait upon the God of my Salvation. My God will he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Mic. 7. 5, 6, 7. A <hi>Contrary</hi> spirit hath entred, which <hi>works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Contrary;</hi> for as the <hi>Spirit</hi> is that <hi>Rules,</hi> so is <hi>Man</hi> in whom it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100369:17"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d whom <hi>it</hi> Leads; and <hi>this is</hi> the <hi>Reason,</hi> and the <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>all</hi> why it is <hi>so;</hi> because that which hath entred into <hi>Man,</hi> is the <hi>Eye, the Foot,</hi> the <hi>Hand,</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> by which <hi>he</hi> sees, <hi>thinks, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>does;</hi> as the <hi>Contrary</hi> Spirit was the <hi>Heart, Eye, Hand and Foot,</hi> before it <hi>was</hi> put under; and when <hi>another</hi> Spirit is entred it is <hi>Put</hi> under. So <hi>Man</hi> is in <hi>Vassalledge</hi> to <hi>that</hi> Spirit, which hath entred, and which <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>suffered so</hi> to do, Over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at which Ruled <hi>him</hi> before, &amp; which had the <hi>Preheminence; which being</hi> entred, <hi>Man</hi> Joyneth with, (yea <hi>Joyned</hi> with <hi>before;</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise it could not have entred; for if <hi>Man</hi> Opened not the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r, Sin</hi> could not <hi>enter)</hi> and so <hi>they</hi> become <hi>One</hi> Flesh; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere is the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Men by <hi>Nature</hi> (the <hi>Nature</hi> that's in the <hi>fall)</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I</hi> have said; and the ground why <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>so</hi> in the <hi>fall;</hi> and of the <hi>entring</hi> of the <hi>fall; Man</hi> consented, <hi>Let</hi> in the <hi>Enemy,</hi> Over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>which</hi> ruled <hi>him</hi> before, and in the <hi>Death</hi> of that, which <hi>he</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rdered for the <hi>Other;</hi> that being entred <hi>rules</hi> Man as did the <hi>Other;</hi> and in <hi>this</hi> state, the <hi>second</hi> Adam finds <hi>all</hi> Men, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Quickning Spirit,</hi> whom the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid in <hi>Sion</hi> a <hi>Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>g Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence; that whosoever believeth in him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not be ashamed.</hi> And thus <hi>he</hi> found <hi>Israel,</hi> and thus it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Israel. They Despised the Pleasant Land,</hi> as hath been <hi>said, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey</hi> believed not <hi>his</hi> Word, (here was the <hi>Ground</hi> of the <hi>Change,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey had Let in the <hi>other,</hi> and consented unto <hi>that,</hi> and given up <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to that,</hi> which was <hi>Contrary</hi> to the <hi>Lord) But murmured in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, and hearkned not unto the Voice of the Lord,</hi> Psal. 105. 7. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e 26.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>what</hi> made the <hi>Stumbling? What</hi> the <hi>Offence? What</hi> made <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> a <hi>Sumbling Stone? What</hi> a <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence?</hi> Against <hi>what</hi> was it? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to <hi>what</hi> was it? and how came it to be <hi>so?</hi> and <hi>what</hi> made it <hi>so?</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Murmuring</hi> spirit; the <hi>Rebellious</hi> spirit; the <hi>spirit</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>back</hi> to <hi>Egypt;</hi> the <hi>spirit</hi> that <hi>Lusted</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness;</hi> that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> God; that <hi>forgat his</hi> Works; that <hi>believed</hi> not in <hi>his</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord; that despised the <hi>Pleasant</hi> Land; that <hi>Strove</hi> with <hi>its</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and smote <hi>him;</hi> that <hi>Envied</hi> Moses, and <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>Saint</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; that made <hi>it a Captain,</hi> and in <hi>its</hi> heart turned <hi>back</hi> unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>This, this</hi> was it <hi>that stumbled; This, this</hi> was it that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>This, this</hi> was it unto which <hi>it</hi> is, was a <hi>Stumbling Stone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a Rock of Offence;</hi> Even that which was sent to deliver <hi>them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to this</hi> it was a <hi>Stumbling Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100369:18"/> would not have had <hi>them</hi> delivered, and which held <hi>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is Bondage, and would have returned <hi>them</hi> thither; and by reason of <hi>this</hi> it came to be <hi>so;</hi> that <hi>they</hi> stumbled at <hi>that Stumbling S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> which was laid in <hi>Sion</hi> for <hi>their</hi> Deliverance; and were <hi>offende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at <hi>it:</hi> It stood in <hi>its</hi> Way to <hi>Egypt;</hi> It stood in <hi>its</hi> Way to <hi>Unbelief;</hi> to <hi>Murmuring,</hi> to <hi>Rebellion.</hi> It told <hi>them they</hi> should not do <hi>so;</hi> that <hi>it</hi> should not make a <hi>Molten</hi> Calf. So <hi>this</hi> Stone <hi>they</hi> could not get <hi>Over</hi> easily, therefore at it <hi>they</hi> stumbled; <hi>This</hi> Rock <hi>they</hi> could not <hi>hew</hi> through, therefore <hi>they</hi> were offended; and <hi>that</hi> was offended, and <hi>that</hi> stumbled, <hi>that</hi> was turned from the <hi>Lord;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> rose up <hi>against</hi> that which the <hi>Lord</hi> had set in <hi>its</hi> Way to stop <hi>them,</hi> in <hi>their</hi> turning from the <hi>Lord;</hi> and to Guide <hi>their</hi> feet in the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>Peace. We will not have this Man to Rule over Us; Who made thee a Judge? and they thrust him from them:</hi> And <hi>that</hi> which made it <hi>so,</hi> and made <hi>them</hi> do <hi>so;</hi> was the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of <hi>Rebelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which had entred <hi>them.</hi> In whose <hi>Way</hi> the <hi>Stone</hi> was <hi>laid,</hi> and the <hi>Rock</hi> planted, to keep <hi>them</hi> from going <hi>thitherwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the <hi>Manner</hi> how <hi>he</hi> comes to be, and is <hi>a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> in all <hi>Ages;</hi> the <hi>Third Questi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and in <hi>Answer</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Wherefore it hath been, (and is so) or the Reason of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Answer, The <hi>Reason</hi> or <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>this</hi> is manifest, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>that</hi> is got into <hi>Man,</hi> and leads <hi>Man</hi> that is an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> stumbles <hi>him,</hi> or makes <hi>him</hi> to stumble at <hi>Every</hi> thing that wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bring <hi>Man</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>therewith</hi> to be <hi>offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it came to pass, that the <hi>Jew</hi> who had the <hi>Law,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Lively Oracles,</hi> being diverted, or perverted from the <hi>right</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>giving</hi> forth of the <hi>Oracles</hi> which was to le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em</hi> to <hi>Christ;</hi> to <hi>Another</hi> thing which was <hi>never</hi> intended by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>giving</hi> forth of the <hi>Law,</hi> or the <hi>Lively</hi> Oracles, to wit, the <hi>se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> up of a <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Own, Or, the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Law</hi> by which <hi>no Man could be Justified;</hi> For, <hi>by the Works of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Law, shall no Flesh be Justified,</hi> saith <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 2. 16. <hi>They stum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> at that Stumbling Stone,</hi> and so <hi>they</hi> attained not unto the <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Righteousness;</hi> who followed after the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness▪ Wherefore?</hi> Because <hi>they</hi> sought it not by <hi>Faith</hi> (saith <hi>he</hi> Even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Israel)</hi> but [as it were] by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> For, (saith <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they stumbled at that stumbling Stone, as it is Written; Behold I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100369:18"/>
               <hi>in Sion a Stumbling Stone, and Rock of Offence; and whosoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him shall not be ashamed,</hi> Rom. 9. 31, 32, 33. But the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> (saith <hi>he,</hi> vers. 30.) <hi>which followed not after Rigbteousness, have attained to Righteousness; Even the Righteousness which is of Faith. And what shall we say then?</hi> saith he, as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Now, the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness</hi> was <hi>Christ;</hi> The <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Righteousness; For Christ is the End of the Law for Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to Every One that believeth,</hi> saith <hi>Paul</hi> again to the <hi>Jews,</hi> of whom <hi>he</hi> also saith; For <hi>I bear them</hi> Record, <hi>that they have a zeal of God, but not according to Knowledge; For they being Ignorant of God's Righteousness, and going about to Establish their Own Righteousness, have not submitted themselves to the Rigtheousness; of God.</hi> For Christ (saith <hi>he) is the End of the Law for Righteousness to every One that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth;</hi> as aforesaid, Rom. 10. 2, 3, 4. For <hi>Moses</hi> (saith <hi>he)</hi> in the <hi>next</hi> Words) <hi>Describeth the Righteousness which is by the Law, that the Man which doth those things shall live by them. But the Righteousness which is of Faith; saith on this wise, Say not in thine heart, who shall ascend into Heaven (that is, to bring Christ down from above) Or, who shall Descend into the Deep?</hi> (that is <hi>to bring Christ again from the Dead.) But what saith it? The Word is nigh thee, Even in thy mouth, and in thy heart; That is, the Word of Faith which we Preach. For if thou shalt confess with thy Mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart, that God hath raised him from the Dead, thou shalt be saved. For with the heart Man believeth unto Righteousness; and with the mouth Confession is made unto Salvation. For the Scripture saith, whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed. For there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Jew, and the Greek, for the same Lord Over all is rich un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that call upon him. For whosoever shall call upon the Name of the Lord shall be saved. How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a Preacher? and how shall they Preach except they be sent? As it is Written, how Beautiful are the feet of them that Preach the Gospel of Peace; and bring glad tydings of Good things? But they have not all obeyed the Gospel. For Isaiah saith, Lord who hath believed Our report? So, then, Faith cometh by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hearing by the Word of God. But I say, have they not heard? Yes, Verily, their found went into all the Earth; and their Words unto the Ends of the World. But I say, Did not Israel know? First, Moses saith, I will provoke them to Jealousie, by them that are no People; and by a foolish Nation, I will Anger you. But Isaiah is very bold and</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100369:19"/>
               <hi>saith; I was found of them that sought me not: I was made manifest unto them that asked not after me. But to Israel he saith, All Day long I have stretched forth my hands unto a Disobedient and Gain-say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People,</hi> Rom. 10. 5. to the end, as aforesaid. <hi>For that which the Law could not do, in that it was Weak through the Flesh. God send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Own Son in the likeness of sinful Flesh, and for Sin Condemned Sin in the Fesh, that the Righteousness of the Law might be fulfilled in Us; who walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit; For, they that are after the Flesh, do mind the things of the Flesh; but they that are after the Spirit, the things of the Spirit; For to be Carnally mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is Death, but to be Spiritually Minded is Life and Peace; because the Carnal Mind is Emnity against God, for it is not subject to the Law of God; Neither indeed, can be so; then they that are in the Flesh cannot please God. But ye are not in the Flesh, but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwell in you. Now, if any Man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his. And if Christ be in you, the Body is Dead because of Sin; but the Spirit is Life because of Righteousness. But if the Spirit of him that raised up Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ from the Dead, Dwell in You; he that raised up Christ from the Dead, also shall quicken your Mortal Bodies by his Spirit that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in You. Therefore Brethren, we are Debtors not to the Flesh, to live after the Flesh; For, if ye live after the Flesh ye shall die; But if ye through the Spirit, do mortifie the Deeds of the Body ye shall live. For, as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God. For, ye have not received the Spirit of Bondage again to fear; but ye have received the Spirit of Adoption whereby we cry Abba Father: The Spirit it self beareth Witness to Our Spirit that we are the Children of God; and if Children, then Heirs, Heirs of God, and Joynt Heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we also may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified together; For, I reckon that the Sufferings of this Present time, are not worthy to be compared with the Glory that shall be Revealed in Us. For, the Earnest Expectation of the Creature, waiteth for the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of the Sons of God. For, the Creature was made subject unto Vanity not willingly, but by reason of him who hath subjected the same in hope: Because the Creature, it self also shall be delivered from the Bondage of Corruption, into the Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God. For, we know that the whole Creation groaneth and Travelleth in pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together until now. And not onely they, but Our selves also who have the first Fruits of the Spirit; Even we Our selves groan within</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100369:19"/>
               <hi>Ourselves, waiting for the Adoption, to wit; The Redemption of Our Body,</hi> Rom. 8. 3. to the 24.</p>
            <p>So then, the <hi>Jew</hi> which followed after the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> attained not unto the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousuess; Christ Jesus</hi> the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Righteousness</hi> to <hi>Every</hi> One that <hi>believeth,</hi> though <hi>they</hi> followed after <hi>him;</hi> How came that to <hi>pass,</hi> Or what was the <hi>Reason?</hi> because <hi>they</hi> sought it not by <hi>Faith;</hi> but as it were by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law:</hi> and what was the <hi>Reason</hi> of that? Because <hi>they</hi> stumbled at the <hi>Stumbling-Stone.</hi> And what was the <hi>Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-Stone?</hi> It was <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness;</hi> the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Righteousness to Every one that Believeth;</hi> which was <hi>laid</hi> in <hi>Sion,</hi> which <hi>they</hi> followed after; at which <hi>they</hi> stumbled; How came <hi>they</hi> to stumble? Because <hi>they</hi> were <hi>besides</hi> the <hi>thing; they</hi> were out of the <hi>Way</hi> of it. <hi>They</hi> sought it as it were by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by which <hi>no Flesh can be Justified</hi> (as aforesaid) and not by the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi> And what was the <hi>Reason</hi> of <hi>that?</hi> Because <hi>Another</hi> thing led <hi>them</hi> then the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> Viz. a <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Own which <hi>they</hi> sought to <hi>Establish,</hi> and so <hi>submitted not unto the Righteousness of God.</hi> Or the <hi>Spirit</hi> which was against the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness, Christ Jesus;</hi> which by <hi>a Righteousness</hi> of <hi>its</hi> Own sought to <hi>Overthrow</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness;</hi> and <hi>so</hi> Deceived <hi>them</hi> which followed after the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> in Leading <hi>them another</hi> way; Yet <hi>as it were</hi> by the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> in the <hi>Way</hi> of which the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> stood; and <hi>that</hi> which sought <hi>it as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> being <hi>another</hi> thing; met with the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> which was <hi>laid</hi> in <hi>their</hi> Way for <hi>them</hi> to follow, Even the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness</hi> which is of <hi>Faith;</hi> and they stumbled at it (see what a <hi>narrow</hi> Path went between <hi>them,</hi> and how the <hi>Enemy</hi> Deceived <hi>them, they</hi> were going against the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> viz. the <hi>Righteousness</hi> which is by <hi>Faith;</hi> whilst <hi>they</hi> thought <hi>they</hi> followed after the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> because <hi>they</hi> sought it <hi>as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by which <hi>no Flesh can be Justified.)</hi> So <hi>there</hi> was the <hi>Miss; their</hi> not following <hi>after</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> by the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> which is by <hi>Faith,</hi> which <hi>saith on this Wise, Say not in thy heart, who shall ascend, into Heaven? (that is, to bring down Christ from above) or who shall Descend into the Deep? (that is to bring up Christ again from the Dead) but what saith it? The Word is nigh thee, Even in thy Mouth, and in thy heart; that is the Word of</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100369:20"/>
               <hi>Faith which we Preach, as</hi> aforesaid; but seeking it by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> and it was but <hi>as it were</hi> neither: For, the <hi>Enemy</hi> dealt with <hi>them,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> did with <hi>Eve</hi> at <hi>first,</hi> not <hi>directly</hi> Leading <hi>them</hi> against the <hi>thing,</hi> then <hi>they</hi> might have perceived <hi>him;</hi> but <hi>as</hi> it <hi>were</hi> by the <hi>thing,</hi> which <hi>as it were,</hi> was <hi>besides</hi> the <hi>thing;</hi> and was <hi>another</hi> way then the <hi>thing</hi> led; and so <hi>he</hi> knew <hi>they</hi> could <hi>never</hi> come at the <hi>thing. Yea, hath God said ye shall not Eat of Every Tree of the Garden? Ye shall not surely Die; for God doth know that in the Day that ye Eat thereof, then your Eyes shall be Opened, and ye shall be as Gods, knowing good, and Evil.</hi> So, <hi>they</hi> sought it by the <hi>Work,</hi> and not by the <hi>thing</hi> that <hi>did</hi> it; and that which led <hi>them</hi> to the <hi>Work,</hi> from the <hi>thing</hi> that <hi>Did</hi> it, to <hi>Work</hi> to <hi>accomplish</hi> the <hi>thing;</hi> without <hi>that</hi> which <hi>Did</hi> the <hi>work;</hi> made <hi>them</hi> to <hi>stumble</hi> at <hi>that</hi> which <hi>Did the Work,</hi> which was <hi>laid</hi> in the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>that which</hi> wrought to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish</hi> the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> without <hi>that</hi> which <hi>Did it.</hi> So the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> was to be <hi>done:</hi> but, <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Righteousness</hi> to <hi>Every One that Believeth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not <hi>seen,</hi> being not <hi>followed,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> nigh <hi>Even in the Mouth, and in the Heart,</hi> (who <hi>Doth all Our</hi> works together in <hi>Us</hi> and for <hi>Us;</hi> and said the <hi>Prophet, Lord thou wilt Ordain Peace for Us, (for thou also hast wrought</hi> all <hi>Our Works in Us,</hi> Isa. 26. 12.) to <hi>Do</hi> the <hi>Work,;</hi> which was the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> to <hi>bring</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Word nigh</hi> in the <hi>Mouth,</hi> and in the <hi>Heart;</hi> and to <hi>believe</hi> in that which <hi>Transgression</hi> had <hi>Covered</hi> Over, and so the <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded because of Transgression: till the Seed should come to whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise was made,</hi> Gal. 3. 19. which <hi>Seed is Christ,</hi> vers. 16. I say, <hi>this</hi> being not <hi>seen, this</hi> being not <hi>followed, this</hi> being not <hi>believed</hi> in, which was the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Righteousness,</hi> the <hi>Promised Seed,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> nigh in the <hi>Mouth,</hi> and in the <hi>Heart,</hi> which <hi>Trangres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> had Covered <hi>Over,</hi> because of which the <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>added, they</hi> stumbled at it; and that which made <hi>them</hi> to stumble, was that which led <hi>them</hi> from <hi>it</hi> to seek <hi>Righteousness, as it were</hi> hy the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> when as the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>Christ;</hi> or to Lead to <hi>Christ,</hi> who <hi>did</hi> the <hi>Work</hi> to <hi>him</hi> that was <hi>nigh</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> written in the <hi>heart;</hi> and the <hi>Fear</hi> in the <hi>Inward Part</hi> which <hi>Sin</hi> had turned <hi>from,</hi> and blotted <hi>out;</hi> and because of <hi>which</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>added; as a School-master to bring unto Christ, the Word</hi> within, not to lead from <hi>him: wherefore the</hi> Law (saith the <hi>Apostle) was Our School-master to bring us unto Christ, that we might be Justified</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100369:20"/>
               <hi>Faith; but after that Faith is come, we are no longer under a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master. For ye are all the Children of God by Faith in Christ Jesus,</hi> Gal. 3. 24, 25, 26. So then, here was the <hi>Narrow</hi> Path; and here <hi>they mist,</hi> and could <hi>never come</hi> (by reason thereof) to that which <hi>they</hi> followed after, to wit, the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>God; they</hi> sought it <hi>as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> when as <hi>they</hi> should have <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> in <hi>that</hi> which did the <hi>Work;</hi> the <hi>Word nigh</hi> in the <hi>Mouth,</hi> and in the <hi>Heart, Christ Jesus,</hi> the <hi>Promised</hi> Seed, which the <hi>Law</hi> was a <hi>School-master</hi> to bring <hi>unto;</hi> and therefore was <hi>added; They</hi> sought it <hi>as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by doing <hi>that</hi> which the <hi>Law</hi> said, and not by <hi>Faith,</hi> by <hi>believing</hi> in <hi>that</hi> which <hi>did</hi> the <hi>Work;</hi> which the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>what</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> said <hi>Pointed</hi> unto, and was the <hi>End</hi> thereof. For, <hi>by the Works of the Law no Flesh can be Justified</hi> (as hath been often said) therefore <hi>God</hi> gave not a <hi>thing as it were</hi> to recover <hi>Man,</hi> or to bring <hi>Man</hi> to that which might recover <hi>him</hi> who was fallen; to plunge <hi>him</hi> into an <hi>Impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the <hi>thing,</hi> that was not <hi>God's</hi> End; but to the End <hi>he</hi> gave it; that it might lead to <hi>him</hi> who did <hi>Recover,</hi> and whom <hi>he</hi> had appointed thereunto; who <hi>did</hi> the <hi>Work</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> required. <hi>For what the Law could not do, it being weak through the Flesh, God sending his Own Son in the likeness of sinful Flesh, and for Sin Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Sin in the Flesh</hi> (here's <hi>the Law of the Spirit of Life, which is in Christ Jesus, which made him free from the Law of Sin, and of Death; as he</hi> saith, Rom. 8. 2.) <hi>that the Righteousness</hi> of the <hi>Law might be fulfilled in Us, who walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit:</hi> as hath been instanced. And at <hi>this</hi> they stumbled; which <hi>lay</hi> in the <hi>Way,</hi> and was <hi>laid</hi> in the <hi>Way</hi> a <hi>Stumbling-Stone</hi> to that which sought <hi>Righteousness</hi> by <hi>Another</hi> thing then by <hi>Faith;</hi> viz. the <hi>Righteousness</hi> which is of <hi>Faith;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> which made <hi>them</hi> to <hi>stumble,</hi> was that which guided <hi>them,</hi> which had deceived <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness</hi> it was, that was the <hi>Stumbling-Stone,</hi> to <hi>that</hi> which sought <hi>Righteousness as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> And <hi>that</hi> which sought <hi>Righteousness as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> was <hi>that</hi> which <hi>stumbled</hi> at that <hi>Stumbling-Stone,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and made <hi>them</hi> stumble thereat, and was the <hi>reason</hi> thereof. And <hi>so Israel which followed after the Law of Righteousness, hath not attained to the Law of Righteousness. Wherefore? because they sought it not by Faith; but as it were by the Works of the Law.</hi> So <hi>they stumbled at that Stumbling-Stone.</hi> And
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100369:21"/> the <hi>Reason,</hi> or the <hi>Ground</hi> of the <hi>thing</hi> was this; Because <hi>Another</hi> thing led <hi>them,</hi> or <hi>they</hi> sought it by <hi>another</hi> Way then the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> the <hi>Righteousness</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which was that which <hi>stumbled</hi> at the <hi>Stumbling Stone,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> which was laid a <hi>Stumbling-Stone</hi> in <hi>Sion,</hi> and a <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence</hi> to <hi>that</hi> which sought it <hi>as it were</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by <hi>which no Flesh can be Justified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>Reason</hi> why <hi>Multitudes</hi> of <hi>People</hi> in <hi>all Ages</hi> have, and at <hi>this</hi> Day do stumble at the <hi>Stumbling Stone,</hi> and strike a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence, Christ Jesus;</hi> who is <hi>laid</hi> in <hi>Sion</hi> a <hi>Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence, that whosoever believeth in him may not be ashamed;</hi> Because <hi>another</hi> thing leads <hi>them,</hi> then <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> which leads <hi>unto him;</hi> though it is <hi>him</hi> that they <hi>mind,</hi> unto which <hi>he is</hi> a <hi>Stumbling Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offence,</hi> and <hi>so</hi> laid of the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> is a <hi>thing</hi> worthy to be <hi>minded,</hi> and it hath in it a <hi>very</hi> great Depth; <hi>Even</hi> the <hi>Reason</hi> why <hi>People</hi> who Profess <hi>Christ,</hi> and speak of <hi>Christ,</hi> and Own in <hi>Words,</hi> and follow after <hi>Christ,</hi> and desire <hi>him,</hi> and Confess that <hi>there</hi> is <hi>no</hi> Salvation without <hi>him;</hi> and <hi>so</hi> Expect <hi>Salvation</hi> from <hi>him,</hi> and yet come <hi>not</hi> at <hi>him,</hi> but are <hi>Enemies</hi> unto <hi>him;</hi> It is because <hi>they</hi> seek not after <hi>him</hi> in the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> but in <hi>Another</hi> Way; and after <hi>Another</hi> Way then <hi>that</hi> which is of <hi>him,</hi> are <hi>they</hi> Guided; which <hi>though</hi> it <hi>seems</hi> to lead to <hi>him,</hi> yet is against <hi>him;</hi> and so <hi>they</hi> are deceived <hi>(many of them) all</hi> their Dayes, till <hi>they</hi> Drop into the <hi>Pit,</hi> and it shut <hi>its Mouth</hi> upon <hi>them.</hi> The <hi>Reason</hi> is, because the <hi>Enemy</hi> that is got in <hi>them,</hi> Covers <hi>Over</hi> the matter, and leads <hi>them hood-winckt</hi> as it were into <hi>Hell,</hi> out of which <hi>there</hi>'s no Redemption, by whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided, <hi>they</hi> savour nothing but what is of <hi>him,</hi> and so run in <hi>Emnity</hi> against <hi>that</hi> which is an <hi>Enemy</hi> unto <hi>him,</hi> Even as <hi>they</hi> are led; and <hi>so</hi> become the <hi>Authors</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Own Destruction.</p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> (in <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>fifth Question,</hi> Viz. <hi>What is the End of the Lord in all, or his Design therein?)</hi> I say, the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>all this,</hi> or <hi>his Design</hi> therein, is, That <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might be saved:</hi> For, the <hi>Lord</hi> seeing the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> in the <hi>fall▪</hi> and how the <hi>Enemy</hi> hath deceived <hi>him,</hi> and leads <hi>him</hi> into the <hi>Pit,</hi> the <hi>Bowells</hi> of the <hi>Lrrd's</hi> Compassion hath regard to <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> state,</hi> and moves unto <hi>him,</hi> and therefore hath placed in <hi>Sun</hi> (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>that</hi> of <hi>himself</hi> in <hi>Man)</hi> a <hi>Stumbling Stone,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>Offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to <hi>this,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> may <hi>stumble</hi> at <hi>this,</hi> and not <hi>get</hi> Over; that <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Rock may be in <hi>his</hi> Way, and <hi>he</hi> may come to Consideration, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100369:21"/>
               <hi>see</hi> where <hi>he is,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> leads <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>whither he</hi> is <hi>going;</hi> and <hi>so</hi> seeing <hi>his</hi> state, <hi>he</hi> may heed that which <hi>is</hi> near to deliver <hi>him;</hi> Even that at which <hi>he stumbles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is <hi>Great</hi> Loving Kindness, and <hi>rich</hi> Mercy of the Lord to <hi>fallen</hi> Man; to deliver <hi>him.</hi> For, <hi>Man</hi> could not have thought of <hi>this,</hi> nor have known in <hi>what</hi> state <hi>he</hi> was, till <hi>he</hi> had been tumbled into the <hi>Pit,</hi> were it not for <hi>this;</hi> and had not the <hi>Lord</hi> set that in <hi>his</hi> Way at which <hi>he</hi> might stumble, whereby <hi>he</hi> might be <hi>awakened,</hi> and know <hi>his</hi> Way, and where <hi>he</hi> is. And this <hi>is</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>all,</hi> an exceeding <hi>high</hi> favour, that, <hi>that</hi> at which <hi>a Man</hi> stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, is <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Truth</hi> is near <hi>ye</hi> People, <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Life;</hi> the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Life;</hi> It is <hi>that</hi> at which <hi>ye</hi> stumble; which <hi>that</hi> leads <hi>ye</hi> to stumble <hi>at,</hi> which leads <hi>ye</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> Yet from it <hi>ye</hi> cannot go; for <hi>God</hi> hath set it in <hi>your</hi> Way, that <hi>ye</hi> might <hi>stumble</hi> at, and be gathered unto <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> is manifest; For, when <hi>ye</hi> go about <hi>Evil,</hi> is there not <hi>something,</hi> and do not <hi>you</hi> find it? that stands in <hi>your</hi> Way, that shews <hi>ye</hi> the <hi>very</hi> Appearance of <hi>Evil,</hi> and seeks to stop <hi>you,</hi> and Checks <hi>you,</hi> and strives with <hi>you;</hi> and Judges <hi>you</hi> when <hi>you</hi> have done it; and calls upon <hi>you,</hi> Saying, <hi>O do not this Abominable thing that my Soul abhorreth. Why will ye Die O house of Israel? As I live saith the Lord, I desire not the Death of a sinner, but rather that he may turn and Live. Hear and your Souls shall Live. The Voice of Wisdom that cryeth without; that Uttereth her Voice in the streets; that cryeth in the chief Place of Concourse; in the Openings of the Gates, in the City; and Uttereth her words; Saying, How long ye Simple Ones will ye love simplicity, and ye scorners delight in their scorning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d fools hate Knowledge; Turn ye at my Reproof. Behold I will pour out my Spirit upon you; I will make known my Words unto you. Because I have called, and ye refused; I have stretched forth my hand, and no man regarded; but ye have set at nought all my Counsel, and would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of my Reproof; I also will laugh at your Calamity; I will mock when your fear cometh, as Disolation, and your Destruction as a Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>; when distress, and anguish cometh upon you. Then shall they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me Early, but they shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> find me; for that they hated Knowledge, and did not choose the Fear of the Lord; They would none of my Counsel; They despised all my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof; Therefore shall they Eat of their Own Way, and be filled with</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100369:22"/>
               <hi>their Own Devices; For the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the Prosperity of Fools shall Destroy them. But who so hearkneth unto me shall dwell safely, and be quiet from the fear of Evil,</hi> Prov. 1. 20. to the end. This is the <hi>Voice</hi> of <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and what <hi>she</hi> speaks, who is in the <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Understanding;</hi> whose <hi>Price</hi> is above <hi>Rubiei; Gold and Precious Stones</hi> is not to be <hi>Compared</hi> with it. The <hi>Fear of the Lord, that is Wisdom, and to depart from Evil, that is Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; The Fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wisdom; A good Ʋ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding have all they that do thereafter: The Praise of it Endures for Ever; and the</hi> hearkning to <hi>this</hi> Delivers from the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>Evil;</hi> and causeth to <hi>Dwell</hi> safely, and to be <hi>quiet</hi> from the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Evil,</hi> but where <hi>this is</hi> not hearkned to, <hi>Destruction</hi> will come, and that <hi>swiftly;</hi> and that which called upon <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>you</hi> would not hear, will not hear <hi>you</hi> when <hi>ye cry,</hi> but will laugh at <hi>your Calamity,</hi> and <hi>mock</hi> when <hi>your</hi> fear cometh as <hi>Desolation,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Destruction as a <hi>Whirlwind;</hi> when <hi>Distress</hi> and <hi>Anguish</hi> cometh upon <hi>you.</hi> Then shall <hi>ye</hi> call on <hi>me</hi> saith <hi>Wisdom,</hi> but <hi>I will</hi> not answer; <hi>ye</hi> shall seek <hi>me</hi> Early, but shall not find <hi>me;</hi> for that <hi>ye</hi> hated Knowledge, and did not choose the <hi>Fear</hi> of the <hi>Lord; Ye</hi> would none of <hi>her</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, <hi>ye</hi> despised all <hi>her</hi> reproof. Therefore shall <hi>ye</hi> Eat of <hi>your</hi> Own Way, and <hi>be</hi> filled with <hi>your</hi> Own Devices. For the <hi>turning away</hi> of the <hi>simple</hi> (the not <hi>hearkening</hi> to, but <hi>turning</hi> from <hi>this Voice</hi> of <hi>Wisdom,)</hi> who <hi>so</hi> calls upon <hi>You,</hi> shall slay <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Prosperity (the <hi>Prosperity</hi> of <hi>fools)</hi> shall destroy <hi>you;</hi> but who <hi>so</hi> hearkneth unto <hi>Wisdom,</hi> (this that <hi>so</hi> calls upon them) shall <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll safely,</hi> and <hi>be</hi> quiet from the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I say, is there not <hi>such</hi> a thing in <hi>you</hi> that reproves, and Judges <hi>you,</hi> that shews <hi>you</hi> Evil, that strives <hi>with you,</hi> that stands <hi>in your</hi> Way, turn <hi>ye</hi> whither soever <hi>ye</hi> will; and so calls upon <hi>you,</hi> so that <hi>ye</hi> cannot do <hi>any</hi> Evil, but <hi>ye</hi> must go against it; <hi>ye</hi> must go Over it, <hi>ye</hi> must stumble at it? And is it not <hi>rich</hi> Loving Kindness, and <hi>great</hi> Mercy that it is <hi>so,</hi> and that it is thus <hi>Long</hi> continued to <hi>you,</hi> and so <hi>many</hi> years? And doth it not concern <hi>you</hi> now at last to mind it, now it is come <hi>so</hi> near you, and made <hi>so</hi> plain unto <hi>you?</hi> And should <hi>ye</hi> not open <hi>your</hi> Eyes, and see <hi>your</hi> way, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and <hi>healed?</hi> And is it not time for <hi>you</hi> to bethink <hi>your</hi> selves, and to consider where <hi>you</hi> are, and to turn unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> who stands in <hi>your</hi> way (and placed <hi>this</hi> for <hi>this</hi> purpose) to turn <hi>you</hi> from Death, into the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Peace?</hi> I am the <hi>Way,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100369:22"/> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> saith <hi>he,</hi> at whom <hi>ye</hi> stumble, who stands in <hi>your</hi> Way to <hi>Evil,</hi> which shews, and reproves it, and is <hi>set</hi> of <hi>God</hi> for <hi>that</hi> purpose. <hi>(Behold this Child is set for the fall, and rising again if many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against; yea a Sword shall pierce through thine Own Soul also, that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed; said the Simeon to the Mary of the Child Jesus,</hi> Luke 2. 34, 35.) He that followes <hi>me shall not abide in Darkness;</hi> should <hi>ye</hi> not hearken unto <hi>this;</hi> should ye not Mind <hi>this?</hi> and be guided by <hi>this?</hi> And is not that <hi>your</hi> Enemy that leads <hi>you</hi> against <hi>this,</hi> and in Opposition to <hi>this;</hi> which stands in <hi>its</hi> Way, and which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid in <hi>yours,</hi> to turn <hi>ye</hi> unto <hi>this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not it a <hi>great</hi> sottishness, and a <hi>high</hi> Degree of stupidity, and <hi>Madness,</hi> for a <hi>Man</hi> to run against <hi>this;</hi> to suffer <hi>himself</hi> to be carryed out against <hi>this;</hi> and the Declaration of <hi>this;</hi> which shews him <hi>this,</hi> and to hate <hi>this;</hi> and to Oppose, and seek to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy <hi>those</hi> whom the Lord hath <hi>sent</hi> to turn <hi>him</hi> unto <hi>this;</hi> to be <hi>so</hi> deceived as to turn against <hi>this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppose a <hi>Man</hi> were in a <hi>fierce</hi> Career in a <hi>Path</hi> unknown to a <hi>Certain</hi> Pit, into which <hi>he</hi> must fall if <hi>he</hi> come unto it; If a <hi>Man</hi> shall stand in <hi>his</hi> Way who sees how it <hi>is,</hi> and seek to hinder <hi>him</hi> that <hi>so</hi> runs, on <hi>Every</hi> hand from running into it; and when <hi>he</hi> puts <hi>here,</hi> and puts <hi>there,</hi> seeking to Avoid <hi>him</hi> that stands in <hi>his Way, he</hi> that <hi>so</hi> stands in <hi>his</hi> Way, still puts before <hi>him</hi> where Ever <hi>he</hi> turns; and seeks to hinder <hi>him,</hi> wheresoever <hi>he</hi> moves, and at length will not suffer <hi>him</hi> that runs to fall into the <hi>Pit,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>he</hi> go Over <hi>him;</hi> and yet <hi>he</hi> will go Over <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>so</hi> fall into the <hi>Pit;</hi> will not <hi>all</hi> Men conclude that hear of <hi>this</hi> thing, that <hi>this</hi> Man was Mad (especially when <hi>he</hi> had full notice of <hi>this</hi> thing, and knew it was <hi>so)</hi> and that <hi>another</hi> spirit led him, then that which is <hi>Natural,</hi> which seeks to preserve the <hi>Body</hi> not to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roy</hi> it? And will not <hi>all</hi> men who shall understand how <hi>his</hi> friend withstood <hi>him</hi> on <hi>Every</hi> hand; and at length would not suffer <hi>him</hi> to fall in till <hi>he</hi> ran Over <hi>him,</hi> Judge, that <hi>that his</hi> friend had done <hi>his</hi> Utmost to keep <hi>him</hi> from the Pit; and that it was <hi>his</hi> Own fault that <hi>he</hi> fell into it?</p>
            <p>Even <hi>so,</hi> when the <hi>Lord</hi> shall set a <hi>Bar</hi> in <hi>your</hi> Way, <hi>ye that</hi> run <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>your</hi> Sin; A <hi>stone</hi> for <hi>You</hi> to <hi>stumble</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; a <hi>Rock</hi> to offend <hi>You;</hi> Or, to fend <hi>You</hi> off; So that, turn on which hand <hi>so</hi> Ever <hi>ye</hi> will,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100369:23"/> there it is, <hi>that</hi> which shews <hi>ye,</hi> that which Judges <hi>You;</hi> this which Checks <hi>You,</hi> that which reproves <hi>You</hi> for Evil, that which strives with <hi>You,</hi> that which stands still in <hi>your</hi> Way, that which seeks to keep <hi>ye</hi> from the <hi>Pit;</hi> Is it not a <hi>Madness</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> and doth not <hi>that</hi> Spirit lead <hi>You</hi> which is in <hi>Opposition</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r Good, and is <hi>your</hi> and <hi>God's</hi> Enemy, and holds <hi>ye</hi> in Captivity, that runs <hi>ye</hi> against <hi>this,</hi> and raises <hi>You at this,</hi> and makes <hi>ye</hi> hate <hi>this,</hi> and the Declaration of this; and sets <hi>ye</hi> against <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>those</hi> who come to shew <hi>ye this;</hi> and whom the <hi>Lord</hi> sends to turn <hi>ye</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>your</hi> Souls may live? And will not <hi>all</hi> knowing Men Judge <hi>ye</hi> to be <hi>so,</hi> and that such a <hi>Spirit</hi> leads <hi>You,</hi> and that <hi>You</hi> are besotted to go <hi>Over this,</hi> and run against <hi>this,</hi> when ye know <hi>ye</hi> should do otherwise, and that <hi>ye</hi> should hearken unto <hi>this,</hi> to that which shews <hi>ye</hi> Evil, and Judges it; and that it is good to hearken unto <hi>it;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> such things lead unto the <hi>Pit,</hi> and that it stands between <hi>You</hi> and <hi>It?</hi> And will not <hi>all</hi> such Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judge, yea, the <hi>Witness</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>You</hi> which is <hi>Privy</hi> unto <hi>all</hi> ye Do, and to <hi>this,</hi> unto which <hi>I</hi> speak, that the Lord could not do <hi>more</hi> (as I may <hi>so</hi> speak) then <hi>he</hi> hath done for you, in placing <hi>something</hi> in <hi>your</hi> Way, thus to withstand <hi>You</hi> to the <hi>Pit,</hi> and to keep <hi>You</hi> out of it; that wheresoever <hi>ye</hi> turn, it stands in <hi>your</hi> way between <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>It;</hi> to turn <hi>ye</hi> from it, to shew <hi>ye</hi> what it is, and how <hi>near,</hi> and to lead <hi>You</hi> into the <hi>Path</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> and will not <hi>they,</hi> and it Judge, that <hi>ye</hi> are left without excuse, and that <hi>your</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction is upon <hi>your</hi> Own heads; yea, doth there not <hi>something</hi> sometimes say <hi>so</hi> in <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>Justifie</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> if <hi>he</hi> should destroy <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>You</hi> heed it not? why, then do <hi>ye</hi> suffer <hi>your</hi> selves to be <hi>thus</hi> deluded by the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Destruction,</hi> from the <hi>Path</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> seeing that it is so near <hi>You,</hi> that which would deliver <hi>You,</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> are upon it; It is <hi>that</hi> at which <hi>ye</hi> stumble, with which <hi>ye</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it is <hi>It?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not time that <hi>your</hi> Eyes were Open; and that <hi>You</hi> saw <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> state, and what an <hi>Enemy</hi> this is that so deludes <hi>You,</hi> and hath <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in Captivity; and whither <hi>ye</hi> are going, and what <hi>ye</hi> are doing; and how <hi>You</hi> are <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>your</hi> Own Peace, and run against <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> friend, and hazard <hi>your</hi> selves for <hi>Ever,</hi> and <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come into consideration, what could the <hi>Lord</hi> have done for Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>he</hi> hath not done? How <hi>many</hi> years hath <hi>he</hi> waited upon <hi>You?</hi> How oft hath <hi>he</hi> warned <hi>You?</hi> How oft hath <hi>he</hi> called upon <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and striven with <hi>You?</hi> How oft hath <hi>he</hi> been refused? How long
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100369:23"/> hath <hi>he</hi> born? Hath <hi>he</hi> need of <hi>You,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> seeks after <hi>You?</hi> Can a Man be Profitable to the <hi>Almighty,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> that is wise may be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>to himself? All my Goodness</hi> (saith David) <hi>Extends not to thee; Every Beast of the Forrest is mine</hi> (saith the <hi>Lord)</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the <hi>Cattle upon a Thousand Hills;</hi> I know <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Fowls</hi> of the <hi>Mountains;</hi> and the <hi>Wild</hi> Beasts of the <hi>Field</hi> are <hi>mine.</hi> If <hi>I</hi> were hungry, <hi>I</hi> would not tell <hi>thee;</hi> for the <hi>whole World is mine,</hi> and the <hi>fulness</hi> thereof, Psal. 50. 10, 11, 12. Psal. 16. 2. Should <hi>he</hi> alwayes then wait on <hi>You,</hi> and <hi>You</hi> will not turn? <hi>(Ye will not come to me</hi> (said <hi>he</hi> to the <hi>Pharisees)</hi> that <hi>ye may have Life)</hi> should <hi>his</hi> Arms be still stretched <hi>open,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> will not be <hi>gathered?</hi> Should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e continually <hi>Call,</hi> and <hi>Cry,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> will not <hi>hear?</hi> Should <hi>he</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes strive, and <hi>ye</hi> will not return? Should he Day after Day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd year after year, stand in <hi>your</hi> way, and <hi>you</hi> will not come at <hi>him?</hi> Do <hi>ye</hi> think this to be <hi>Civil</hi> among <hi>Men, Sober,</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able?</hi> Do <hi>You</hi> know <hi>ye</hi> have need of <hi>him?</hi> Is <hi>your</hi> Breath in <hi>your</hi> Nostrils? Can <hi>ye</hi> Create a thought? Is not <hi>your Life</hi> a Vapour? <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> Day a <hi>span</hi> Long? Can <hi>ye</hi> tell what will be <hi>to</hi> Mortow? What will be <hi>next</hi> moment? Can <hi>ye</hi> cause the <hi>Air</hi> to breath, or the <hi>Wind</hi> to blow, or the <hi>Sun</hi> to shine? Can <hi>ye</hi> give Life to <hi>any</hi> thing? Know <hi>ye</hi> your Own Life, Or, what is in <hi>You?</hi> Are <hi>You</hi> sure of <hi>One</hi> Breath more? Can <hi>ye</hi> make <hi>your</hi> Cloathes to warm <hi>You,</hi> or <hi>your</hi> me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to give <hi>You</hi> nourishment? Can <hi>ye</hi> slumber <hi>once,</hi> or give it when sleep's gone from <hi>your</hi> Eyes? Can <hi>ye bring</hi> the <hi>Morning;</hi> or <hi>hasten</hi> the <hi>Night?</hi> Are <hi>You</hi> sure the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> after <hi>all</hi> your Denyals, will strive <hi>once</hi> more with <hi>You?</hi> If it <hi>strive</hi> no more (that which Judges <hi>You;</hi> that which reproves <hi>You;</hi> that which calls upon <hi>You;</hi> that which Checks you; that which shews <hi>ye</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> should do) what then will <hi>ye</hi> do? What then will become of <hi>You? I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> punish your Daughters when they commit Whoredom; Nor your Spouses when they commit Adultery. Ephraim is given to Idols, Let him alone. Thou shalt not be a Reprover to this People; Pray not for this People; Nor lift up a Prayer for them; Neither make Interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for them, for I will not fear thee. This I will do unto you, I will Even forsake you; and Wo unto you, when I depart from you.</hi> Do <hi>ye</hi> well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en to Tempt the <hi>Lord?</hi> Are <hi>ye</hi> stronger then <hi>he?</hi> Can <hi>ye</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem <hi>your</hi> Souls from the <hi>Grave;</hi> Or <hi>your</hi> Life from the <hi>Pit?</hi> Is it not a Price <hi>too</hi> great for <hi>You,</hi> and ceaseth it not for <hi>Ever?</hi> Can <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> bear <hi>his</hi> Wrath for <hi>Ever,</hi> and <hi>Ever,</hi> for a <hi>Moment?</hi> Is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to step into <hi>Eternity,</hi> in a <hi>Moment,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> know not <hi>whither;</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100369:24"/> Nor <hi>where?</hi> Will not <hi>his</hi> Wrath sinck <hi>ye</hi> in a <hi>Moment?</hi> Can <hi>ye</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> sumptuous then to put <hi>all</hi> upon a <hi>Breath;</hi> and yet <hi>ye</hi> know not wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Go? Can <hi>ye</hi> trifle <hi>it thus</hi> with Eternity, and be without <hi>Sence,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Lord,</hi> and Tempt the <hi>holy</hi> One of <hi>Israel?</hi> If <hi>he</hi> cut <hi>ye</hi> down, are <hi>ye</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Will <hi>ye</hi> not be <hi>tumbled</hi> into the <hi>Pit</hi> out of which <hi>ye</hi> cannot <hi>come?</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> time for <hi>You</hi> to bethink <hi>your</hi> selves? Is it not time to look about <hi>You?</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> time to <hi>Mind?</hi> Is it not time to <hi>Consider?</hi> Is it not <hi>high</hi> time for <hi>You</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out of <hi>sleep,</hi> least <hi>ye sleep the sleep of Death,</hi> and never <hi>rise</hi> more will <hi>ye</hi> Do, if <hi>ye</hi> are undone for <hi>Ever? No</hi> Pitty then, <hi>No</hi> Compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>your</hi> hour i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Over, when the <hi>Door</hi> is shu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it is <hi>too</hi> late, call while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Lord, Lord, Open to Ʋs; He</hi> will say <hi>I know ye not;</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> stri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Door</hi> is shut, whilst <hi>he</hi> strives there is <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe</hi> the <hi>Door</hi> is <hi>Open</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whilst <hi>he</hi> Calls; <hi>To Day whilst it is called to Day, if You will hear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> harden not your hearts, as in the Day of Provocation; Make</hi> hast; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Give <hi>your</hi> Eyes no rest; Nor <hi>your</hi> Eye Lids slumber, till <hi>You</hi> have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> surance, (how small soever if it be true) that it is well with <hi>You</hi> as to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>Eternall▪</hi> It's the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> whether <hi>You</hi> will hear; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>You</hi> will forbear. Time is <hi>short,</hi> yea <hi>very</hi> short: Yet a <hi>very</hi> little whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will <hi>all</hi> be concluded with the <hi>God</hi> whom <hi>ye</hi> serve. <hi>Mock</hi> not; <hi>stand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Awe</hi> before <hi>God;</hi> Hear <hi>his</hi> Voice; Know the <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Visitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> member <hi>You</hi> were warned; Yet a <hi>little</hi> while, and <hi>You</hi> shall know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> means; <hi>Remember the Lord a far off;</hi> Draw near unto <hi>him.</hi> As <hi>little</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Ever</hi> had <hi>Age,</hi> or <hi>Generation,</hi> is <hi>this</hi> of <hi>yours; Repent, Draw</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whilst <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcy</hi> is on the <hi>Knee</hi> (as it were) whilst <hi>Salvation</hi> seeks <hi>You (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of them that sought me not; I was made manifest to them that aske<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me,</hi> Rom. 10. 20.) Least <hi>your</hi> Day <hi>close</hi> up, (and 'tis <hi>closing)</hi> and <hi>Nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> You,</hi> and you <hi>never</hi> see <hi>Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord makes things <hi>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> plain to <hi>You; He</hi> comes <hi>very near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> knowes what is <hi>near;</hi> It's good for <hi>You</hi> to come to <hi>him;</hi> It's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>You</hi> to hear; <hi>He</hi> would not have <hi>You</hi> Die; <hi>He</hi> rather would t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> turn and <hi>Live, he</hi> hath sworn it; There is <hi>something</hi> in it, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> concerns <hi>ye</hi> to Mind; There's something in <hi>You</hi> that's <hi>Eternall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> never</hi> Die; that cannot be Destroyed, so as that it shall ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but it shall <hi>Live</hi> in <hi>Eternal</hi> Wo, or <hi>Joy</hi> Everlasting; Have <hi>Pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> have <hi>Pitty</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> selves, <hi>Run</hi> nor <hi>headlong</hi> into <hi>Destructio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> not an <hi>Enemy</hi> that <hi>seeks</hi> nothing but to undo <hi>You,</hi> who is not pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>You; He</hi> would have <hi>You</hi> tormented with <hi>him</hi> for <hi>Ever</hi> and <hi>Ever; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> good</hi> for <hi>You;</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> knowes it; and what it will be; and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to save <hi>You;</hi> and puts a <hi>Stumbling Stone</hi> in <hi>your</hi> way, and a <hi>Roc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to stop <hi>You,</hi> to send <hi>You</hi> off in <hi>your</hi> Career to <hi>Hell,</hi> to the <hi>Pit</hi> of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bears</hi> off, It stands in <hi>your</hi> way, the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>set</hi> it <hi>there</hi> for that purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it <hi>stands; Heed</hi> it; <hi>Let</hi> it shew <hi>You</hi> the <hi>way</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> It is the <hi>way</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>it;</hi> For, <hi>yet a very</hi> little while, and <hi>time</hi> shall be <hi>no</hi> more; your <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> done, and closed upon <hi>You.</hi> It is the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> unto <hi>You,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bristoll.</hi>
                  <date>27th. 10th. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GEO. BISH<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>